[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Civilian aircraft mainly focuses on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) defense",
            "b) maneuvering",
            "c) climb of altitude",
            "d) coverage of distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Civilian aircraft mainly focuses on distance coverage. Civilian aircraft looks for making profit by managing fuel consumption. This is because it doesn’t need to perform any attacking maneuvers. A civilian aircraft is more preferred when it gives guaranteed safety for the passengers and also by offering luxury facilities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The surveillance aircraft focuses on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) maneuvering",
            "b) attack",
            "c) high altitude and cover long distance",
            "d) speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two types of mission profiles. They are civilian mission profile and military mission profile. A civilian mission profile focuses on fuel consumption and distance covered whereas a military mission profile focuses on endurance and speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "What is the full form of STOL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short take-off and landing",
            "b) Straight take-off and landing",
            "c) Smart take-off and landing",
            "d) Supportive take-off and landing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A military aircraft is not designed to be luxurious and entertaining. Military aircraft mainly focuses on military maneuvers. A military aircraft is generally preferred to maintain high altitude and perform various military maneuvers at higher altitudes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "What is the full form of VTOL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variety take-off and landing",
            "b) Vertical take-off and landing",
            "c) Various take-off and landing",
            "d) Valuable take-off and landing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The purpose of surveillance aircraft is to maintain high altitude and cover an estimated distance of flight in the given period of time. A surveillance aircraft doesn’t need to perform any kind of maneuvering or attack other aircrafts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "What is the full form of STVOL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smart take-off and variety landing",
            "b) Smart take-off and vertical landing",
            "c) Short take-off and variety landing",
            "d) Short take-off and vertical landing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of STOL is Short take-off and landing. STOL must also be able to stop within 1,500 feet after crossing a 50-foot obstacle on landing. This kind of landing is helpful in harsh landing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CTOL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Commercial take-off and landing",
            "b) Convenient take-off and landing",
            "c) Convectional take-off and landing",
            "d) Confidential take-off and landing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of VTOL is Vertical take-off and landing. This kind of aircraft can take-off, hover and land vertically. Helicopters come under this category.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "What effect does high density altitude have on aircraft performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease in climb performance",
            "b) Increase in climb performance",
            "c) Increase in take-off performance",
            "d) Increase in engine performance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The full form of STVOL is Short take-off and vertical landing. Mostly fixed-wing aircrafts come under this category. STOVL performance of an aircraft is the ability of an aircraft to take off and clear a 50-foot obstruction in a distance of 1,500 feet from beginning the takeoff run and land vertically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "What is meant by reserves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel used when the route is extended",
            "b) Fuel used to take-off",
            "c) Fuel used when in emergency",
            "d) Fuel used while cruising"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The full form of CTOL is Convectional take-off and landing. These aircrafts take-off and land involving the use of runway. Passenger aircraft come under this category.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "The stages of mission profile of a commercial aircraft are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Take-off → climb → cruise → descent → landing",
            "b) Take-off → descent → climb → cruise → landing",
            "c) Take-off → cruise → climb → descent → landing",
            "d) Take-off → climb → descent → cruise → landing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  There will be a decrease in climb performance with increase in high density altitude. On increase of altitude there would be a decrease in density which results in decrease in power output of engine and airfoil efficiency, as a result there will be a decrease in climb increase performance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "What is meant by performance estimation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prediction of capabilities of the aircraft",
            "b) Provide validated performance data for performance section",
            "c) Verification of aircraft achievements",
            "d) Certification of performance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Performance estimation involves the prediction of the capabilities of the aircraft from the consideration of its aerodynamic design, powerplant and operating environment. It is applied to design, modification and supplement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not applied to performance estimation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design",
            "b) Modification",
            "c) Supplement",
            "d) Validation of performance data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  d\nExplanation: Performance estimation is applied in fields of design of a new type of aircraft, modification of an existing aircraft type in respect to design changes affecting its aerodynamic characteristics and to supplement or extend the full-scale measured performance of an aircraft type for conditions outside those already established.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "ISA stands for_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Standard Atmosphere",
            "b) International Standard Altitude",
            "c) International Standard Airlines",
            "d) International Standard Aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ISA stands for International Standard Atmosphere International Standard Atmosphere (ISA) is a linearized model of the temperature atmosphere. It represents the mean global atmosphere state with respect to seasonal changes and latitude and is used as the basis for aircraft design.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "International Standard Atmosphere (ISA) is a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linearized Model of the Temperature Atmosphere",
            "b) Horizontal Model of the Temperature Atmosphere",
            "c) Linearized Model of the Pressure Atmosphere",
            "d) Horizontal Model of the Pressure Atmosphere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The performance estimation process begins with the proposal of some performance target. Such as the requirement to carry a specified payload over a given route that forms the mission profile, possibly within time and cost limits.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "The performance estimation process is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) optional",
            "b) iterative",
            "c) not required",
            "d) single attempt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The elimination process will include an assumption of the environmental conditions of the atmosphere in which the aircraft will operate. Since the atmosphere is a very variable medium in that its pressure and temperature vary with height and also with geographical location and time. Performance estimation is based on assumption of International Standard Atmosphere (ISA).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "_________ is the important factor to be satisfied during performance estimation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Airworthiness requirement",
            "d) Climate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: International Standard Atmosphere (ISA) is a linearized model of the temperature atmosphere. It represents the mean global atmosphere state with respect to seasonal changes and latitude and is used as the basis for aircraft design.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "WAT stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight, Altitude, Temperature",
            "b) Weather,Altitude, Temperature",
            "c) Weight, Atmosphere, Temperature",
            "d) Weather,Atmosphere, Temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: WAT stands for Weight, Altitude, Temperature. Data measured in flight are measured under the arbitrary WAT conditions existing at the time. The flight –measured data will need to be processed to conform to specific combinations of WAT for the construction of the performance manual.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "ODM stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operation Data Manual",
            "b) Operating Data Manual",
            "c) Operation Data Management",
            "d) Operating Digital Manual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ODM stands for Operating Data Manual. Operating Data Manual (ODM) contains the information on the performance of the aircraft needed by the operator for flight planning above the ground.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is meant by performance measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verification of aircraft achievements",
            "b) Design new type of aircraft",
            "c) Modification of existing aircraft type",
            "d) Supplementor extent the full-scale measured performance of an aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ODM stands for Operating Data Manual. Operating Data Manual (ODM) contains the information on the performance of the aircraft needed by the operator for flight planning above the ground.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which of the following is applied to performance measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design",
            "b) Modification",
            "c) Supplement",
            "d) Validation of performance data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Performance measurement is the process of verification of aircraft estimations in design performance, to demonstrate that the aircraft can satisfy the safety criteria set down in the airworthiness requirements, to provide validated performance data for the performance section of the flight manual.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "APMS stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aviation Performance Measurement System",
            "b) Aviation Performance Measuring System",
            "c) Aircraft Performance Measuring System",
            "d) Aircraft Performance Measurement System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Performance measurement is the process of verification of aircraft estimations in design performance, to demonstrate that the aircraft can satisfy the safety criteria set down in the airworthiness requirements, to provide validated performance data for the performance section of the flight manual.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "FAA stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fundamental Aviation Administration",
            "b) Federal Aircraft Administration",
            "c) Federal Aviation Administration",
            "d) Fundamental Aircraft Administration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: APMS stands for Aviation Performance Measuring System. APMS is an advanced software analysis tool used in flight-data analyses. It is mostly preferred for safety and to increase fight reliability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "AFM stands for ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Authority of Flight Manual",
            "b) Aircraft Flight Manual",
            "c) Aircraft Flight Management",
            "d) Authority of Flight Management"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FAA stands for Federal Aviation Administration. FAA is a national aviation agency of the US. This was formed after the formation of ICAO in the early 1970’s. The functions of FAA is to look after the safety, air traffic and follow the five degrees of freedom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "POH stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pilot’s Operational Handbook",
            "b) Pilot’s Operating Handbook",
            "c) Performance Operating Handbook",
            "d) Performance Operational Handbook"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: AFM stands for Aircraft Flight Manual. It is also known as Pilot’s Operating Handbook (POH). It contains the operating data such as climb, take-off and range data of the aircraft. Few changes had to be done by the user or check for those variations to make the data useful.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "AIAA stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Australian Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics",
            "b) Alberta Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics",
            "c) Andaman Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics",
            "d) American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: POH stands for Pilot’s Operating Handbook. It contains the operating data such as climb, take-off and range data of the aircraft. Few changes had to be done by the user or check for those variations to make the data useful.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "MTOW stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum permissible Take-Off Weight",
            "b) Minimum permissible Take-Off Weight",
            "c) Maximal permissible Take-Off Weight",
            "d) Minimal permissible Take-Off Weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Factors that the affect aircraft performance during take-off are mass of the aircraft during take-off, air density, temperature and runway conditions. The speed of wind and flap setting and airframe contamination are the other factors that affect the aircraft performance during take-off.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What is operational performance of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The performance of an aircraft which is related to the aircraft above ground level",
            "b) The performance of an aircraft which is related to the aircraft engine",
            "c) The performance of an aircraft which is related to the aircraft when it is on ground",
            "d) The performance of an aircraft which is related to the aircraft taxing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MTOW stands for Maximum permissible Take-Off Weight.  MTOW  is the maximum weight of an aircraft at which a pilot is allowed to take-off the aircraft. This is caused due to structural limits of the aircrafts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "What is MTOW of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The maximum weight of an aircraft at which a pilot is allowed to attempt to land the aircraft",
            "b) The maximum weight of an aircraft at which a pilot is allowed to attempt to take-off the aircraft",
            "c) The minimum weight of an aircraft at which a pilot is allowed to attempt to take-off the aircraft",
            "d) The minimum weight of an aircraft at which a pilot is allowed to attempt to land the aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The basic requirements for safe flight are that the space required for the aircraft to maneuver should never exceed the space available this is because if the space is insufficient for the aircraft to perform a maneuver then there may be a failure of the aircraft due to this aircraft getting hindered by some factor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "A flight is carrying 130 passengers over a distance of 990km with a seating capacity of 140 and a yield of 7.9. Calculate the load factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90%",
            "b) 92.86%",
            "c) 89.556%",
            "d) 67.35%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Operational performance of an aircraft is the performance of an aircraft which is related to the aircraft above ground level. It includes aircraft cruise angle, altitude, temperature, engine failure, fuel management and also take-off performances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "A flight is carrying 130 passengers over a distance of 990km with a seating capacity of 140 and a yield of 7.9. Calculate the passenger revenue.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 143780",
            "b) 1016730",
            "c) 1094940",
            "d) 1524263"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aircraft weight is the only controllable variable that can be used to ensure that space required for the maneuver doesn’t exceed the space available. As a rule of aircraft performance the space required for an aircraft to maneuver must be always less than the space available. As a result the aircraft weight much be checked to avoid complications that occur due to space required being more than space available.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "A flight is carrying 130 passengers over a distance of 990km with a seating capacity of 140 and a yield of 7.9. Calculate the Revenue passenger kilometers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 138600",
            "b) 124570",
            "c) 128700",
            "d) 124560"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MTOW stands for Maximum permissible Take-Off Weight.  MTOW is the maximum weight of an aircraft at which a pilot is allowed to take-off the aircraft. This is caused due to structural limits of the aircrafts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "A flight is carrying 130 passengers over a distance of 990km with a seating capacity of 140 and a yield of 7.9. Calculate the available seats kilometer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 148700",
            "b) 138600",
            "c) 128700",
            "d) 154800"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The answer is 92.86%. Given number of passengers travelling = 130, seating capacity=140 and a yield of 7.9.\nWe know percentage load factor=\\(\\frac{no. \\, of \\, passengers \\,travelling*distance \\,travelled}{no. \\,of \\, seats*distance \\, travelled}\\) x 100%\nOn substituting the values,\nLoad factor=\\(\\frac{130*990}{140*990}\\) x 100%\nLoad factor=92.86%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "What is the ideal gas equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P=nRT",
            "b) PV=nRT",
            "c) PV=ρRT",
            "d) Pρ=RT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ideal gas equation is PV=ρRT, where\nP=pressure of gas (Units=N/m2)\nV=volume of gas (Units=m3)\nρ=density of gas (Units=Kg/m3)\nR=universal gas constant (Units=Nm/kg-K)\nT=temperature of gas (Units=K).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the major reason for the global atmosphere pressure distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Convective air flow",
            "b) Conductive air flow",
            "c) Radiation air flow",
            "d) Conductive and radiation air flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Between the poles and the equator the mean global temperature roughly follows a sine curve. This is due to the changes of temperature near the equator and the poles. At the equator the mean seasonal variation is small and the mean temperature is high whereas at the poles the mean seasonal variation is large and the mean temperature is low.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "What is meant by Coriolis force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An earth force that tends to deflect the moving objects on earth",
            "b) An earth force that tends to vary the temperature",
            "c) An earth force that tends to vary the pressure",
            "d) An earth force that tends to vary the gravitational force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The convective air flow is the major reason for the global atmosphere pressure distribution. The Coriolis forces cause the air flow to swirl and create a series of convectional current cells which results in the general pattern of high and low pressure region over the surface of the earth.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Which of the following holds a correct relation between pressure, temperature and altitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure increases, temperature decreases, altitude increases",
            "b) Pressure decreases, temperature decreases, altitude increases",
            "c) Pressure decreases, temperature increases, altitude increases",
            "d) Pressure decreases, temperature decreases, altitude decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coriolis force is an earth force that acts perpendicular to the direction of motion and to the axis of rotation. This force tends to deflect moving objects to the left in the southern hemisphere and towards the right in the northern hemisphere.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "What are the percentages of nitrogen, oxygen, argon and carbon dioxide in atmosphere?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 78%, 21%, 0.9%, 0.03%",
            "b) 75%, 24%, 0.7%, 0.03%",
            "c) 71%, 28%, 0.9%, 0.04%",
            "d) 75%, 24%, 0.9%, 0.05%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the pressure decreases there will be a temperature decreases during an increase in altitude. This is based on ideal gas equation PV=nRT where,\nP=pressure of gas (Units=N/m2)\nV=volume of gas (Units=m3)\nρ=density of gas (Units=Kg/m3)\nR=universal gas constant (Units=Nm/kg-K)\nT=temperature of gas (Units=K).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "What is the value of characteristic gas constant(R) in Nm/kg-K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 287.05287",
            "b) 2.8705287",
            "c) 2870.5287",
            "d) 2.8705287"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The percentages of nitrogen, oxygen, argon and carbon dioxide in atmosphere are 78%, 21%, 0.9%, 0.03%. The atmosphere also consists of other inert gases, dust particles, water vapor and moisture in minute quantities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "The ratio of specific heats (γ) of air is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.6",
            "b) 1.7",
            "c) 1.4",
            "d) 1.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of characteristic gas constant(R) is 287.05287 Nm/kg-K and the value of universal gas constant (R0) is 8.3145 J/mol. The relation between them is R=\\(\\frac{R0}{M}\\) , where R0 is universal gas constant; R is characteristic gas constant and M is molecular weight of the substance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "According to ISA atmospheric model what is the value of datum atmospheric pressure in N/m2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 101325",
            "b) 101335",
            "c) 101336",
            "d) 101326"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ratio of specific heats (γ) of air is 1.4. Ratio of specific heats is the ratio of specific heat of air at constant pressure to the specific heat of air at constant volume, i.e. \\(\\frac{C_p}{C_v}\\)=γ. Cp of air is 1.008 kJ/kg-K; Cv of air is 0.721 kJ/kg-K at standard levels. So γ=\\(\\frac{1.008}{0.721}\\)=1.4.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "The atmosphere is mainly divided into _______ layers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The atmosphere is divided into 5 layers. They are troposphere, stratosphere, mesosphere, thermosphere and exosphere where these layers are sub divided into lower and upper layers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "According to ISA atmospheric model what is the value of datum atmospheric temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 273K",
            "b) 277K",
            "c) 288.15K",
            "d) 288.15°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to ISA atmospheric model what is the value of datum atmospheric temperature is 288.15K. It can also be written as 15.15°C. The relation between Kelvin scale and Celsius scale is K=°C+273.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "The range of temperature in mesosphere is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) below 130K",
            "b) below 140K",
            "c) below 110K",
            "d) below 120K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of temperature in mesosphere is below 130K. It starts at the top of stratosphere and ends at mesopause. It is the coldest part of earth’s atmosphere. It is usually around 85 to 100 kilometers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "The range of temperature in thermosphere is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200-500°C",
            "b) 200-1000°C",
            "c) 200-2000°C",
            "d) 200-700°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The range of temperature in thermosphere is 200-2000°C. The temperature varies from day and night, during night its 200°C and during day it’s 200°C. The upper thermosphere extends up to a temperature of 2000°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The range of temperature in stratosphere is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) -51°C  to -15°C",
            "b) -5°C  to -10°C",
            "c) -510°C  to -105°C",
            "d) -31°C  to -10°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of temperature in stratosphere is -51°C  to -15°C. The layer closer to tropopause is -51°C and the layer close to mesosphere is -15°C. This temperature change happens depending on seasonal changes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "The range of temperature in troposphere is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15°C  to -51°C",
            "b) 5°C  to -10°C",
            "c) 510°C  to -105°C",
            "d) 31°C  to -10°C"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of temperature in troposphere is 15°C  to -51°C. Troposphere is quite cool compared to other atmospheric layers of earth. Troposphere has higher temperature than stratosphere.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "The altitude range of thermosphere is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50km to 400km",
            "b) 90km to 500km",
            "c) 100km to 300km",
            "d) 70km to 400km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The altitude range of thermosphere is 90km to 500km. Thermosphere is present between mesosphere and exosphere. The range of temperature in thermosphere is 200-2000°C. The temperature varies from day and night, during night its 200°C and during day it’s 200°C. The upper thermosphere extends up to a temperature of 2000°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "The altitude range of troposphere is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10km to 50km",
            "b) 8km to 18km",
            "c) 20km to 60km",
            "d) 10km to 30km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The altitude range of troposphere is 8km to 18km. The tropopause is about 18km above the equator. The height of the troposphere varies with seasons, it is highest in summer and lowest in winter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "The altitude range of mesosphere is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40km to 80km",
            "b) 30km to 50km",
            "c) 50km to 85km",
            "d) 40km to 70km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The altitude range of mesosphere is 50km to 85km. Mesosphere is present between stratosphere and thermosphere. The temperature in this region constantly decreases with increase in altitude.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "The altitude range of stratosphere is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20km to 70km",
            "b) 18km to 50km",
            "c) 10km to 50km",
            "d) 30km to 40km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The altitude range of stratosphere is 18km to 50km. Stratosphere extends to an altitude of about 50km above earth’s surface. Stratosphere is above troposphere.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct order of atmospheric layers with respect to altitude increase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exosphere < Thermosphere < Mesosphere < Stratosphere < Troposphere",
            "b) Thermosphere < Stratosphere < Mesosphere < Troposphere < Exosphere",
            "c) Troposphere < Stratosphere < Mesosphere < Thermosphere < Exosphere",
            "d) Troposphere < Stratosphere < Mesosphere < Exosphere  < Thermosphere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct order of atmospheric layers with respect to altitude increase is troposphere < Stratosphere < Mesosphere < Thermosphere < Exosphere. The altitude range of troposphere is  8km to 18km. The altitude range of stratosphere is 18km to 50km. The altitude range of mesosphere is 50km to 85km. The altitude range of thermosphere is 90km to 500km. The altitude range of exosphere is 500km to 10000km.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "The altitude range of exosphere is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400km to 1000km",
            "b) 500km to 1000km",
            "c) 500km to 10000km",
            "d) 500km to 5000km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The altitude range of exosphere is 500km to 10000km. The exosphere is the topmost layer of earth and next to this starts the outer space of solar system. This region has a temperature of 1700°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "According to ISA atmospheric model what is the value of datum atmospheric air density kg/m3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.225",
            "b) 12.225",
            "c) 1.23",
            "d) 1.000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: International Standard Atmosphere is based on the assumption that air is a perfect gas and obeys gas law. It also neglects the effects of dust, water vapour and moisture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "The temperature-height profile is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) T=Ti+Li (H-Hi)",
            "b) T=Ti+Li (H+Hi)",
            "c) T=Ti-Li (H-Hi)",
            "d) T=Ti-Li (H+Hi)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to ISA atmospheric model what is the value of datum atmospheric air density is 1.225 kg/m3. It can also be written as 1225 g/m3 else 1.225 x 10-9 kg/mm3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "What is lapse rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Change of temperature with respect to altitude",
            "b) Change of temperature with respect to pressure",
            "c) Change of pressure with respect to altitude",
            "d) Change of temperature with respect to density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The temperature-height profile is given by T=Ti+Li (H-Hi), where\nT= temperature\nTi=temperature at lower boundary layer at that height\nLi=lapse rate\nH=height\nHi=height at lower boundary layer at that height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "What is true height?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The vertical geometrical distance between an object and a datum level",
            "b) The vertical geometrical distance between a certain height and a datum level",
            "c) The horizontal geometrical distance between an object and a datum level",
            "d) The horizontal geometrical distance between a certain height and a datum level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lapse rate is the change of temperature with respect to altitude. The temperature lapse rate is linear at tropopause to stratosphere. The lapse rate is zero in from the altitude 11km to 20km. The temperature lapse rate becomes positive at the middle of stratosphere.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "What is the hydrostatic equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ΔP=-ρg∆h",
            "b) ΔP=-ρgh",
            "c) P=-ρgΔh",
            "d) ΔP=ρgΔh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True height is the vertical geometrical distance between an object and a datum level. It is denoted by –z. Unit of true height is meter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "What is the pressure difference across a cylinder which consists of water and has a height difference of 20m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -196.2 kN/m2",
            "b) -1.962×10-5 bar",
            "c) -196.2 kN/m2",
            "d) -1.962×10-5 bar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hydrostatic equation is given by ΔP=-ρg∆h. This equation is derived from equating force acting on a cylindrical flow. The unit of pressure is N/m2. It can also be represented in atm, bar, Pascal.\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "The pressure-height relationship in troposphere is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\)=[1 + \\(\\frac{L_0}{T_0}\\)H]\\(\\frac{-g_0}{RL_0}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\)=[1 + \\(\\frac{L_0}{T_0}\\)H]\\(\\frac{-T_0}{RL_0}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\)=[1 + \\(\\frac{g_0}{T_0}\\)H]\\(\\frac{-g_0}{RL_0}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\)=[1 + \\(\\frac{L_0}{g_0}\\)H]\\(\\frac{-g_0}{RL_0}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The answer is -196.2 kN/m2.\nGiven Δh=20m, g=9.81m/s2, ρ=1000kg/m3.\nFrom ΔP=-ρg∆h,\nΔP=-1000*9.81*20\nΔP=-196200 N/m2 or ∆P=-196.2 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "What is relative pressure at 101325 N/m2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: True height is the vertical geometrical distance between an object and a datum level whereas the geopotential height is the vertical coordinate referenced to earth’s mean sea level and the difference between true height and geopotential height is relatively small.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "What is relative temperature at 241.45K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0.8379",
            "c) 0.8774",
            "d) 0.8756"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pressure-height relationship in troposphere is given by \\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\)=[1 + \\(\\frac{L_0}{T_0}\\)H]\\(\\frac{-g_0}{RL_0}\\) , where\np=pressure\np0=datum pressure\nL0=lapse rate\nT0=datum temperature\ng0=acceleration due to gravity\nH=height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "What is relative temperature at 1600ft? (T1600=284.98 K)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.989",
            "b) 0.838",
            "c) 0.877",
            "d) 0.999"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Any atmosphere that does not conform to the ISA profile is referred to as an off-standard atmosphere. In this atmosphere there are no assumptions taken as in that of ISA tables.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "What is relative pressure at 1600ft? (P1600=95602 N/m2)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.9453",
            "b) 0.9858",
            "c) 0.9435",
            "d) 0.9595"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 1.\nGiven p=101325 N/m2,\nFrom relative pressure (δ)=\\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\) \nδ=\\(\\frac{101325}{101325}\\)=1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "What will be the pressure-height ratio of air at an altitude of 9144m? (L0=-0.0065 K/m, T0=288.15K, P0=101325 N/m2)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.297",
            "b) 0.596",
            "c) 0.359",
            "d) 0.458"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The answer is 0.8379.\nGiven T=241.45K,\nFrom relative temperature (θ)=\\(\\frac{T}{T_0}\\) \nθ=\\(\\frac{241.45}{288.15}\\)=0.8379.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "ADD stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airflow Direction Detector",
            "b) Aircraft Direction Detector",
            "c) Airflow Density Detector",
            "d) Aircraft Density Detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ADD stands for airflow direction detector. The function of airflow direction detector is to sense the local flow direction relative to the aircraft body axes and these are the part of the aircraft system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "ADC stands for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aircraft Data Computer",
            "b) Air Data Computer",
            "c) Air Density Computer",
            "d) Air Data Computation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The essential requirement of air data measurement is the state of the atmosphere in which the aircraft is flying. The second essential requirement of air data measurement is the relative motion between the aircraft and the air mass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "1 knot=________km/hr",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.773",
            "b) 1.852",
            "c) 1.609",
            "d) 1.414"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The essential requirement of air data measurement is the relative motion between the aircraft and the air mass. The second essential requirement of air data measurement is the state of the atmosphere in which the aircraft is flying.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "1 foot=_________meters",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.28084",
            "b) 0.3678",
            "c) 0.3048",
            "d) 3.4567"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ADC stands for air data computer. This is a device installed in aircraft to convert pressure into electrical signals. The conversion is done with the help of transducers which help in processing the electrical signals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Which of the following are measured by Pitot – static system in air data system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Height, mach number, airspeed",
            "b) Pressure, density, temperature",
            "c) Height, mach number, pressure",
            "d) Height, mach number, density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ADC is an electrical power based system and not a pure mechanical instrument. ADC stands for air data computer. This is a device installed in aircraft to convert pressure into electrical signals. The conversion is done with the help of transducers which help in processing the electrical signals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "What is meant by altimeter reading?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the reading of individual mechanical instrument which calculates the pressure",
            "b) It is the reading of individual electrical instrument which calculates the pressure",
            "c) It is the reading of individual mechanical instrument which calculates the density",
            "d) It is the reading of individual electrical instrument which calculates the density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Altimeter reading is the reading of individual mechanical instrument which calculates the pressure. During these calculations some corrections are made to avoid errors that are caused due to mechanical tolerance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is meant by indicated altitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the pitot-static reading corrected for performance error",
            "b) It is the altimeter reading corrected for instrument error",
            "c) It is the pitot-static reading corrected for instrument error",
            "d) It is the altimeter reading corrected for performance error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Indicated altitude is the altimeter reading corrected for instrument error. The indicated altitude will be measured with reference to the appropriate altimeter datum pressure setting.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "What is meant by pressure altitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the indicated altitude measured with respect to appropriate datum pressure setting",
            "b) It is the indicated altitude measured with respect to appropriate gauge  pressure setting",
            "c) It is the indicated altitude measured with respect to appropriate static pressure setting",
            "d) It is the indicated altitude measured with respect to appropriate vacuum pressure setting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Altimeter indicates the height as a function of barometric static pressure in the atmosphere. Altimeter reading is the reading of individual mechanical instrument which calculates the pressure. During these calculations some corrections are made to avoid errors that are caused due to mechanical tolerance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "What is meant by geopotential height interval?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the pressure height interval measured by the pitot-static tube",
            "b) It is the pressure height interval measured by the altimeter",
            "c) It is the temperature height interval measured by the pitot-static tube",
            "d) It is the temperature height interval measured by the altimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pressure altitude it is the indicated altitude measured with respect to appropriate datum pressure setting. It is corrected for static pressure error. This error is caused due to the static source being located within the disturbed pressure field caused due to presence of aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "The geopotential height of the isothermal lower stratosphere (i.e. at 11km) is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) H=11000-\\(\\frac{RT_{11}}{g_0}\\)ln(\\(\\frac{p}{p_{11}}\\)) ",
            "b) H=11000-\\(\\frac{RT_{11}}{g_0}\\)ln(\\(\\frac{p_{11}}{p}\\)) ",
            "c) H=11000+\\(\\frac{RT_{11}}{g_0}\\)ln(\\(\\frac{p}{p_{11}}\\)) ",
            "d) H=11000+\\(\\frac{RT_{11}}{g_0}\\)ln(\\(\\frac{p_{11}}{p}\\))"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Geopotential height interval it is the pressure height interval measured by the altimeter. Geopotential height interval is corrected for temperature difference from ISA model atmosphere.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Find the geopotential height of an aircraft flying sea level where L0=-0.0065 k/m, p=30070.36Pa.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9120 km",
            "b) 9144 km",
            "c) 9854 km",
            "d) 9874 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The height of the isothermal lower stratosphere is given by H=11000-\\(\\frac{RT_{11}}{g_0}\\)ln(\\(\\frac{p}{p_{11}}\\)) where,\nH=geopotential height\nR=characteristic gas constant\nT11=temperature at 11km\nP11=pressure at 11km\ng0=acceleration due to gravity\np=pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "8.The geopotential height in troposphere is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) H=\\(\\frac{T_0}{l_0}\\)[(\\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\))\\(\\frac{-L_0R}{g_0}\\)+1] ",
            "b) H=\\(\\frac{T_0}{l_0}\\)[(\\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\))\\(\\frac{L_0R}{g_0}\\)-1] ",
            "c) H=\\(\\frac{T_0}{l_0}\\)[(\\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\))\\(\\frac{-L_0R}{g_0}\\)-1] ",
            "d) H=\\(\\frac{T_0}{l_0}\\)[(\\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\))\\(\\frac{L_0R}{g_0}\\)+1]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The answer is 9144 km. Given L0=-0.0065 k/m, p=30070.36 Pa.\nWe know T0=288.15K, p0=101325Pa, R=287 J/kg-K, g0=9.81m/s2.\nFrom H=\\(\\frac{T_0}{l_0}\\)[\\((\\frac{p}{p_0})^\\frac{-L_0R}{g_0}\\)-1] \nH=\\(\\frac{288.15}{-0.0065}\\)[\\((\\frac{30070.36}{101325})^\\frac{-(-0.0065)*287}{9.81}\\)-1] \nH=9144 km.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "What is a barometric altimeter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A device used to measure the height above a fixed level with the help of barometric pressure changes",
            "b) A device used to measure the pressure above a fixed level with the help of barometric pressure changes",
            "c) A device used to measure the height above a fixed level with the help of pitot tube pressure changes",
            "d) A device used to measure the pressure above a fixed level with the help of pitot tube pressure changes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The geopotential height in troposphere is given by H=\\(\\frac{T_0}{l_0}\\)[(\\(\\frac{p}{p_0}\\))\\(\\frac{-L_0R}{g_0}\\)-1] where\nH=geopotential height\nR=characteristic gas constant\nT0=temperature at 11km\nP0=pressure at 11km\ng0=acceleration due to gravity\np=pressure\nL0=lapse rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "What is the relation between pressure and density in an adiabatic air flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=(\\(\\frac{\\rho_1}{\\rho_2}\\))\\(\\frac{1}{\\gamma}\\)",
            "b) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=(\\(\\frac{\\rho_1}{\\rho_2}\\))γ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=(\\(\\frac{\\rho_1}{\\rho_2}\\))γ+1",
            "d) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=(\\(\\frac{\\rho_1}{\\rho_2}\\))γ-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relation between pressure and density in an adiabatic air flow is given by \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=(\\(\\frac{\\rho_1}{\\rho_2}\\))γ where p1, p2 are pressure values and ρ1, ρ2 are density values and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What is meant by airspeed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The relative velocity between the aircraft and the air mass in which the aircraft is flying",
            "b) The ratio of velocity between the aircraft and the air mass in which the aircraft is flying",
            "c) The relative acceleration between the aircraft and the air mass in which the aircraft is flying",
            "d) The ratio of velocity between the aircraft and the ground in which the aircraft is flying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Airspeed is the relative velocity between the aircraft and the air mass in which the aircraft is flying. The unit of airspeed is knot. There are different types of airspeeds. They are ground speed, true airspeed, calibrated airspeed and indicated airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the general equation that relates flow temperature to true airspeed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CpT+\\(\\frac{V^2}{2}\\)=constant",
            "b) CpT-\\(\\frac{V^2}{2}\\)=constant",
            "c) CvT+\\(\\frac{V^2}{2}\\)=constant",
            "d) CvT-\\(\\frac{V^2}{2}\\)=constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Airspeeds are of four types. They are ground speed, true airspeed, calibrated airspeed and indicated airspeed. Airspeed is the relative velocity between the aircraft and the air mass in which the aircraft is flying. The unit of airspeed is knot.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "What is true airspeed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) relative speed of aircraft with respect to the surrounding air flow",
            "b) relative speed of aircraft sound with respect to the surrounding air flow sound",
            "c) moment of aircraft with respect to air",
            "d) moment of aircraft with respect to ground"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CpT+\\(\\frac{V^2}{2}\\)=constant is the general equation that relates flow temperature to true airspeed, where Cp=specific heat at constant pressure, T=temperature, V=true airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "TAS stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) true air speed",
            "b) temperature air speed",
            "c) troposphere air speed",
            "d) thermal air speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True airspeed is the relative speed of aircraft with respect to the surrounding air flow. As the altitude increases the pressure decreases and the true airspeed is greater than indicated airspeed. It is also represented as TAS.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": " IAS stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) inductor air speed",
            "b) indicated air speed",
            "c) induced air speed",
            "d) isentropic air speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TAS stands for true air speed. True airspeed is the relative speed of aircraft with respect to the surrounding air flow. As the altitude increases the pressure decreases and the true airspeed is greater than indicated airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "GS stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gravitational speed",
            "b) greater speed",
            "c) ground speed",
            "d) gradual speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IAS stands for indicated air speed. Indicated air speed is the speed indicated on the airspeed indicator in the cockpit. Airspeeds are of four types. They are ground speed, true airspeed, calibrated airspeed and indicated airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "CAS stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) calculated air speed",
            "b) casual air speed",
            "c) crucial air speed",
            "d) calibrated air speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: GS stands for ground speed. Ground speed is the relative movement between the aircraft and the ground. It is corrected for true air speed. For example, 98 knots true air speed + 10 knots tailwind=108 knots ground speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct relationship between R and Cp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R=Cp\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{\\gamma}\\) ",
            "b) Cp=R\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{\\gamma}\\) ",
            "c) R=Cp\\(\\frac{\\gamma+1}{\\gamma}\\) ",
            "d) Cp=R\\(\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CAS stands for calibrated air speed. Calibrated air speed is the indicated air speed corrected for the instrument and positional errors. Airspeeds are of four types. They are ground speed, true airspeed, calibrated airspeed and indicated airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct relationship between γ and Cv?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cv=R\\(\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) ",
            "b) Cv=\\(\\frac{R}{\\gamma-1}\\) ",
            "c) Cv=\\(\\frac{R}{\\gamma+1}\\) ",
            "d) Cv=R\\(\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma\\mp1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R=Cp\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{\\gamma}\\) is the correct relationship between R and Cp where R= characteristic gas constant, γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume and Cp is the specific heat at constant pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for speed of sound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt{\\gamma RT}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sqrt{pRT}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sqrt{\\rho Rt}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sqrt{\\gamma R0T}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct formula for speed of sound is \\(\\sqrt{\\gamma RT}\\) where R=characteristic gas constant, T=temperature and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "What is the speed of sound in air at an altitude where temperature is 299K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 346.61K",
            "b) 343.61K",
            "c) 71.61 °C",
            "d) 70.61 °C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 346.61K. Given T=299K. We know that R=287J/kg-K, γ for air is 1.4.\nFrom a=\\(\\sqrt{\\gamma RT}\\) \na=\\(\\sqrt{1.4*287*299}\\) \na=346.61K.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": " What is the relation between pressure and air speed in isentropic relations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=\\(\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(\\frac{V1}{a1})^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=\\(\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}(\\frac{V1}{a1})^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma+1}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=\\(\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}(\\frac{V1}{a1})^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=\\(\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(\\frac{V1}{a1})^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma+1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relation between pressure and air speed in isentropic relations is\n\\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=\\(\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(\\frac{V1}{a1})^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) where p1, p2 are pressures at two points, V1=velocity at one point, a1=speed of sound at point one and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "What is the pressure ratio of an aircraft moving in air at a mach number 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.893",
            "b) 1.558",
            "c) 1.444",
            "d) 1.555"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 0.458. Given M=1. We know γ of air is 1.4. From \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) \nOn substituting the values \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{1.4-1}{2} 1^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{1.4}{1.4-1}\\) \n \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=1.893.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "What is the pressure ratio of an aircraft moving in air at a velocity 500m/s and speed of sound is 244 m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.556",
            "b) 3.327",
            "c) 6.256",
            "d) 2.565"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The answer is 0.458. Given V=500m/s, a=244m/s. We know γ of air is 1.4. From  \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=\\(\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(\\frac{V1}{a1})^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) \nOn substituting the values \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{500}{244}\\Big\\}^\\frac{1.4}{1.4-1}\\) \n\\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}\\)=3.327.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct isentropic relation between pressure and temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=(\\frac{T_2}{T_1})^\\frac{\\gamma}{1-\\gamma}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=(\\frac{T_2}{T_1})^\\frac{\\gamma-1}{\\gamma}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=(\\frac{T_2}{T_1})^\\frac{\\gamma+1}{\\gamma}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=(\\frac{T_2}{T_1})^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=(\\frac{T_2}{T_1})^\\frac{\\gamma}{1-\\gamma}\\)   is the correct isentropic relation between pressure and temperature where p1, p2 are pressures, T1, T2 are temperatures and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "What is the speed of sound where density and pressure are 1.225kg/m3 and 101306N/m2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 340.26m/s",
            "b) 330.26m/s",
            "c) 313 m/s",
            "d) 325 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 340.26m/s. Given P=101306N/m2, ρ=1.225kg/m3 and we know that γ for air is 1.4. From the formula, a=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma P}{\\rho}}\\) \na=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma*101306}{1.225}}\\) \na=340.26m/s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "What is the formula for speed of sound in terms of pressure and density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) a=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma P}{\\rho}}\\) ",
            "b) a=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma\\rho}{P}}\\) ",
            "c) a=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma RP}{\\rho}}\\) ",
            "d) a=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma P}{\\rho R}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for speed of sound in terms of pressure and density is given by a=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma P}{\\rho}}\\) where a=speed of sound, P=pressure, ρ=density and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "What is the relation between equivalent air speed and pressure ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ve=V\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\) ",
            "b) Ve=\\(\\frac{V}{\\sqrt{\\sigma}}\\) ",
            "c) Ve=Vσ2",
            "d) Ve=Vσ-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ve=V\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\) is the relation between equivalent air speed and pressure ratio where Ve is the equivalent air speed, V=velocity and σ is pressure ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "What is the equivalent air speed where velocity is 330m/s and pressure ratio is 8.447?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 959.1m/s",
            "b) 1000m/s",
            "c) 981m/s",
            "d) 954m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 959.1m/s. Given V=330m/s, σ=8.447. From the equation Ve=V\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\) \nVe=330\\(\\sqrt{8.447}\\) \nVe=959.1m/s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "What is equivalent air speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The calibrated air speed corrected for scale-altitude error",
            "b) The true air speed corrected for scale-altitude error",
            "c) The indicated air speed corrected for scale-altitude error",
            "d) The ground air speed corrected for scale-altitude error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Equivalent air speed is the calibrated air speed corrected for scale-altitude error. The correction is done in calibrated equation of the airspeed indicator which is a function of calibrated air speed and height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the full-law calibration equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pp-p=p0\\(\\Bigg[\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\left(\\frac{V_c}{a_0}\\right)^2\\Big\\}^{\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}}-1\\Bigg]\\) ",
            "b) pp-p=p0\\(\\Bigg[\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}\\left(\\frac{V_c}{a_0}\\right)^2\\Big\\}^{\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}}-1\\Bigg]\\) ",
            "c) p-p0=p0\\(\\Bigg[\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\left(\\frac{V_c}{a_0}\\right)^2\\Big\\}^{\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}}-1\\Bigg]\\) ",
            "d) pp-p=p0\\(\\Bigg[\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\left(\\frac{V_c}{a_0}\\right)^2\\Big\\}^{\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma+1}}-1\\Bigg]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full-law calibration equation is  pp-p=p0\\(\\Bigg[\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\left(\\frac{V_c}{a_0}\\right)^2\\Big\\}^{\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}}-1\\Bigg]\\) where pp, p, p0 are pressures, Vc is calibrated air speed and a0 is speed of sound and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "What is the formula for mach number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) M=\\(\\frac{V}{a}\\) ",
            "b) M=\\(\\frac{a}{V}\\) ",
            "c) V=\\(\\frac{a}{M}\\) ",
            "d) a=\\(\\frac{M}{V}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The formula for mach number is M=\\(\\frac{V}{a}\\) where M=mach number, V=velocity, a=speed of sound. There is no unit for mach number as it is a ratio of speed of the object to the speed of sound in the surrounding air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "What is the mach number of an aircraft flying with a speed of 450m/s at a temperature of 290 K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.318",
            "b) 2.045",
            "c) 3.214",
            "d) 0.235"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The answer is 1.318. Given T=290K , V= 450m/s. We know γ of air=1.4 and R=287 J/kg-K.\nFrom the formula-M=\\(\\frac{V}{a}\\) where a=\\(\\sqrt{\\gamma RT}\\) \nOn substituting the values to find “a”,\nwe have a=\\(\\sqrt{1.2*287*290}\\) \na=341.35m/s.\nNow substituting the value of “a” in the formula=\\(\\frac{V}{a}\\), \nwe get M=\\(\\frac{450}{341.35}\\) \nM=1.318.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct relation for mach number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) M=V\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\rho}{\\gamma P}}\\) ",
            "b) V=\\(\\frac{a}{M}\\) ",
            "c) M=V\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{P}{\\gamma\\rho}}\\) ",
            "d) M=V\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\gamma p}{\\rho}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: M=V\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\rho}{\\gamma P}}\\) is the correct relation for mach number in terms of pressure and density. In M=V\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\rho}{\\gamma P}}\\), M=mach number, V=velocity , ρ=density, P= pressure and γ is γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "What is the mach number of an aircraft flying in air at a pressure of 101306N/m2 and velocity 556m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.634",
            "b) 2.145",
            "c) 0.125",
            "d) 1.225"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 1.634. Given P=101306N/m2, V=556m/s. We know that ρ and γ of air are ρ=1.225kg/m3 and 1.4. From the equation M=V\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\rho}{\\gamma P}}\\) \nOn substituting and solving,\nM=556\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{1.225}{1.4*101306}}\\) \nM=1.634.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is the relation between mach number and pressure ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{p1}{p2}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{p2}{p1}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{p1}{p2}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{p1}{p2}=\\Big\\{1-\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relation between mach number and pressure is \\(\\frac{p1}{p2}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) where p1, p2 are pressures at two points, M=mach number and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "What is the mach number of aircraft flying in air where the pressure ratio is 1.893?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The answer is 1. Given σ=1.893 and we know that γ for air is 1.4.\nOn substituting the values in the equation \\(\\frac{p_1}{p_2}=\\Big\\{1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{\\gamma}{\\gamma-1}\\) \nWe get 1.893=\\(\\Big\\{1+\\frac{1.4-1}{2}(M)^2\\Big\\}^\\frac{1.4}{1.4-1}\\) \nOn solving we get M=1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "What is the relationship between temperature and mach number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T0=T\\(\\Big[1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}M^2\\Big]\\) ",
            "b) T0=T\\(\\Big[1+\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}M^2\\Big]\\) ",
            "c) T0=T\\(\\Big[1-\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}M^2\\Big]\\) ",
            "d) T0=T\\(\\Big[1-\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}M^2\\Big]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mach number of an aircraft is affected by the shock waves created at the vortex of the aircraft. There are three types of shock waves they are normal shock waves, oblique shock waves and expanded waves.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": " What will be the temperature of aircraft flying in air where the stagnation temperature is 288.15K and mach number is 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250.15K",
            "b) 240.125K",
            "c) 300K",
            "d) 270.18K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relationship between temperature and mach number is T0=T\\(\\Big[1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}M^2\\Big]\\) where T is the temperature at that altitude, T_0 is the stagnation temperature, M is mach number and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expression for recovery factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) r=\\(\\frac{T_i+T}{T_t+T}\\) ",
            "b) r=\\(\\frac{T_i-T}{T_t-T}\\) ",
            "c) r=\\(\\frac{T_i+T}{T_t-T}\\) ",
            "d) r=\\(\\frac{T-T_i}{T+T_t}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of indicated temperature rise to ideal pressure rise is known as recovery factor. It is given by the expression r=\\(\\frac{T_i-T}{T_t-T}\\) where r is known as recovery factor, Ti is known as indicated total temperature, Tt is known as total temperature and T is known as static temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "What is the recovery factor if the total temperature is equal to the indicated total temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) -1",
            "d) -2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The expression for recovery factor is given by r=\\(\\frac{T_i-T}{T_t-T}\\) where r is known as recovery factor, Ti is known as indicated total temperature, Tt is known as total temperature and T is known as static temperature. The ratio of indicated temperature rise to ideal pressure rise is known as recovery factor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "What is the relation between speed of object and temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T0=T\\(\\Big[1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(\\frac{V}{a})^2\\Big]\\) ",
            "b) T0=T\\(\\Big[1-\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(\\frac{V}{a})^2\\Big]\\) ",
            "c) T0=T\\(\\Big[1+\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}(\\frac{V}{a})^2\\Big]\\) ",
            "d) T0=T\\(\\Big[1-\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}(\\frac{V}{a})^2\\Big]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 1. The expression for recovery factor is given by r=\\(\\frac{T_i-T}{T_t-T}\\)where r is known as recovery factor, Ti is known as indicated total temperature, Tt is known as total temperature and T is known as static temperature. In the formula if Tt=Ti then\nr=\\(\\frac{T_i-T}{T_i-T}\\) \nr=1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "What is the relation between recovery factor and temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ti=T[1+r\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\)M2] ",
            "b) Ti=T[1+r\\(\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}\\)M2] ",
            "c) Ti=T[1-r\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\)M2] ",
            "d) Ti=T[1-r\\(\\frac{\\gamma+1}{2}\\)M2]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relation between speed of object and temperature is T0=T\\(\\Big[1+\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}(\\frac{V}{a})^2\\Big]\\)  where T is the temperature at that altitude, T0 is the stagnation temperature, γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume, V is speed of object and ‘a’ is speed of sound.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What is the indicated temperature of an aircraft having mach number 2 and when temperature and recovery factor are 300K and 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 780K",
            "b) 128K",
            "c) 345K",
            "d) 435K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relation between recovery factor and temperature is Ti=T[1+r\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\)M2] where T is the temperature at that altitude, Ti is indicated total temperature, r is recovery factor, M is Mach number and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "What is the mach number of the aircraft which is moving in air at an indicated total temperature is 780K and the temperature, recovery factor at that point are 300K and 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 0.1",
            "d) 0.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 780K. Given r=2, T=300K, M=2 and we know that γ for air is 1.4. From the formula Ti=T[1+r\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\)M2].\nOn substituting the values we get Ti=300[1+2\\(\\frac{1.4-1}{2}\\)22] \nOn solving above equation we get Ti=780K.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Calculate the indicated temperature rise when indicated total temperature is 400K and temperature at that point is 389K.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11",
            "b) 5.5",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The answer is 2. Given r=2, T=300K, Ti=780K and we know γ of air is 1.4. From the formula Ti=T[1+r\\(\\frac{\\gamma-1}{2}\\)M2].\nOn substituting the values in the formula, we get 780=300[1+2\\(\\frac{1.4-1}{2}\\)M2].\nOn solving we get M=2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Calculate the ideal temperature rise when total temperature is 440K and temperature at that point is 369K.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 71",
            "b) 70",
            "c) 75",
            "d) 78"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The difference in indicated values and local values of altitude, airspeed and mach number is known as system pressure error. The indicated values of the altitude, airspeed and mach number resulting from the measured values of the local or system, pressures will differ from the values that would occur when using the undisturbed freest stream pressures. This error is known as system pressure error.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "FSO stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full-scale output",
            "b) Flight-scale output",
            "c) Flight stimulation output",
            "d) Full screen output"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FSO stands for full-scale output. At a specific temperature the variation in output signals as the transducer performs over a range from minimum to maximum pressure is known as full-scale output.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for dynamic pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) q=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)γPM2",
            "b) q=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)γρM2",
            "c) q=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)γPV2",
            "d) q=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)γρV2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transducers are the pressure devices used to convert signal in one form of energy to another energy form. Pressure transducers can also be called as transmitters, senders, indicators or piezometers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Calculate the dynamic pressure of aircraft in air when mach number and pressure are 2 and 101325N/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 283710 N/m2",
            "b) 541278 N/m2",
            "c) 352769 N/m2",
            "d) 457815 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Air data computer system measures airspeed, mach number, temperature and height. Air data computer is an important avionic component present in an aircraft that measures airspeed, mach number, temperature and height with the help of pitot-static tube.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Calculate the dynamic pressure of aircraft in air when density and flow speed are 1.23 kg/m3 and 340m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 71094 N/m2",
            "b) 54128N/m2",
            "c) 65487 N/m2",
            "d) 65789 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dynamic pressure is the difference between stagnation pressure and static pressure. In simpler way it is kinetic energy per unit volume of a fluid particle. It is represented by ‘q’. The formula for dynamic pressure is given by q=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)γPM2 where q=dynamic pressure, P is pressure of the fluid, M is mach number of that medium and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Find the flow speed of air when the dynamic pressure is 70516 N/m2 and density is 1.23kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 338.62 m/s",
            "b) 340 m/s",
            "c) 313.5 m/s",
            "d) 321.5 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct formula for dynamic pressure is q=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)γPM2 where q=dynamic pressure, P is pressure of the fluid, M is mach number of that medium and γ is the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to that of specific heat at constant volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a correct equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fa+Fp+Fg=Fl",
            "b) Fa+Fp+Fg=Fl",
            "c) Fa+Fp+Fg=Fl",
            "d) Fa+Fp+Fg=Fl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct equation is Fa+Fp+Fg=Ft where Fa=aerodynamic forces, Fp=propulsive forces, Fg=gravitational forces and Fl=inertial forces. The statement says that the system of forces containing gravitational forces, aerodynamic forces and propulsive forces results in the inertial forces acting on the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "What is the basic assumption taken in formulating equations of motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All the engines will operate at equal gross thrust",
            "b) All the engines do not operate at equal gross thrust",
            "c) All the engines will operate at equal gross drag",
            "d) All the engines do not operate at equal gross drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The system of forces acting on the aircraft are propulsive forces, aerodynamic forces, gravitational forces and these result in inertial forces. From Newton’s law the equation becomes Fa+Fp+Fg=Ft where Fa=aerodynamic forces, Fp=propulsive forces, Fg=gravitational forces and Fl=inertial forces.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the additional assumption taken in the derivation of the equations of motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gross thrust acts in aircraft body axis",
            "b) Thrust component is small compared to lift component",
            "c) Aircraft is in symmetric flight",
            "d) Rate of change of mass is neglected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The basic assumption taken in formulating equations of motion is all the engines will operate at equal gross thrust. There are other assumptions also taken in the case of convectional aircraft there are:\n\nRate of change of mass is neglected\nAircraft is in symmetric flight\nGross thrust acts in aircraft body axis\nTotal net thrust is T cosα-DM\nThrust component is small compared to lift component.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "The total thrust force assumed in the derivation of equations of motion is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FN=T cosα+DM",
            "b) FN=T cosα-DM",
            "c) T cosα=DM-FN",
            "d) DM=T cosα+FN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The aircraft is symmetrical flight during the derivation of equations of motion.The other assumptions taken are:\n\nRate of change of mass is neglected\nAircraft is in symmetric flight\nGross thrust acts in aircraft body axis\nTotal net thrust is T cosα-DM\nThrust component is small compared to lift component. \n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Excess thrust in the longitudinal equations of motion is given by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FN+D",
            "b) FN-D",
            "c) D-FN",
            "d) FN*D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total thrust force assumed in the derivation of equations of motion is FN=T cosα-DM where FN=net thrust force, T is thrust force, cosα is lift component and DM is drag force acting downwards.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "What is the function of excess thrust in longitudinal equations of motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease the potential energy and kinetic energy",
            "b) Increase the potential energy and kinetic energy",
            "c) Decrease the potential energy and increase kinetic energy",
            "d) Increase the potential energy and decrease kinetic energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In static performance the acceleration of the flight is zero. In this case the resulting conditions are proved to be as: \n\nThrust is equal to drag and\nLift is equal to weight of the aircraft.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "In which of the following terms the forces of aircraft must be considered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aircraft weight, flight mach number, altitude",
            "b) Aircraft weight, airspeed, altitude, temperature",
            "c) Aircraft weight, flight mach number, temperature",
            "d) Aircraft weight, airspeed, altitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inertial forces from the mass of the aircraft and its acceleration. The inertial forces act in the velocity axis system. Inertial forces are a result of gravitational forces, aerodynamic forces and propulsive forces. Numerically it is given by Fa+Fg+Fp=Fi.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the forces that are concerned with the performance of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lift, drag, weight",
            "b) Lift, drag, side force",
            "c) Lift, drag",
            "d) Lift, drag, weight, side force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gravitational force is the product of mass of the aircraft and its acceleration. It is represented by Fg. It is described as the downward pulling force of the earth. It is also referred as W=mg. It can also be written as Fg=mg=W.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for reynolds number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Re=\\(\\frac{\\rho Vl}{\\mu}\\) ",
            "b) Re=\\(\\frac{PVl}{\\mu}\\) ",
            "c) Re=\\(\\frac{\\rho \\mu l}{V}\\) ",
            "d) Re=\\(\\frac{\\rho Vl}{P}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aerodynamic forces arise from the relative motion between the aircraft and the air mass in which it is flying. It is represented by Fa. The aerodynamic forces include lift, weight, drag and thrust.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The range of Re in the typical flight is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 106 to 109",
            "b) 105 to 109",
            "c) 106 to 108",
            "d) 106 to 1010"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An aircraft forces are described in terms of aircraft weight, flight mach number, altitude rather than in terms of aircraft weight, airspeed, altitude, temperature. In this the altitude becomes a basic variable of the aerodynamic forces.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "What is the range of mach number for a conventional aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 to 3.2",
            "b) 0 to 2.2",
            "c) 0 to 4.2",
            "d) 0 to 1.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lift, drag, side force are the forces that are concerned with the performance of an aircraft. The lift and drag forces play a crucial role in the performance of an aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "What is the critical mach number for most subsonic aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Around 0.8",
            "b) Around 2",
            "c) Around 1",
            "d) Around 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct formula for reynolds number is given by Re=\\(\\frac{\\rho Vl}{\\mu}\\) where Re is Reynolds number, ρ is density of the fluid, V is the velocity of the fluid, l is the length of the fluid and μ is the dynamic viscosity of the fluid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for lift of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)ρV2SCl",
            "b) L=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)V2SCl",
            "c) L=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)ρV2Cl",
            "d) L=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)PV2SCl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct formula for lift of an aircraft is L=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)ρV2SCl where L is lift, ρ is density, V stands for velocity of the aircraft, S is span and Cl is coefficient of lift. Lift is one of the fundamental aerodynamic force that is caused for the upward movement of the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "What is the theoretical value of lift curve slope of a flat airfoil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2π per radian",
            "b) 4aπ per radian",
            "c) 3π per radian",
            "d) π per radian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The zero-lift angle of attack is zero if the aerofoil is symmetric. The zero-lift angle of attack is represented by α0. For symmetric airfoil the α0=0. For asymmetric airfoil the α0≠0. In the case of cambered airfoil the value of α0 is negative.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "What is meant by stalling angle of attack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The angle at which we get maximum lift",
            "b) The angle at which we get maximum drag",
            "c) The angle at which we get minimum lift",
            "d) The angle at which we get minimum drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of cambered airfoil the value of α0 is negative. The zero-lift angle of attack is zero if the aerofoil is symmetric. The zero-lift angle of attack is represented by α0. For symmetric airfoil the α0=0, for asymmetric airfoil the α0≠0.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a correct condition when the angle of attack is beyond stalling angle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drag is greater than lift",
            "b) Weight is less than lift",
            "c) Drag is less than lift",
            "d) Weight is less than thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The theoretical value of lift curve slope of a flat airfoil is 2π per radian i.e. \\(\\frac{dC_l}{d\\alpha}\\)=0 here \\(\\frac{dC_l}{d\\alpha}\\) is lift curve slope. This factor is depending on thickness of the airfoil and aspect ratio. The lift curve slope is directly proportional to thickness and inversely proportional to aspect ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "What is the value of Cl of a symmetric airfoil if the angle of attack is 5°?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.548",
            "b) 0.0548",
            "c) 3.1416",
            "d) 31.416"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lift curve slope is directly proportional to thickness and inversely proportional to aspect ratio. The lift slope curve is given by \\(\\frac{dC_l}{d\\alpha}\\). The theoretical value of lift curve slope of a flat airfoil is 2π per radian i.e. \\(\\frac{dC_l}{d\\alpha}\\)=0.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "What is stall buffet condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an aerodynamic vibration caused due to separation or turbulent airflow",
            "b) it is a condition in which the separation is laminar",
            "c) It is a condition in which the flow separation is not considered",
            "d) It is a condition in which the turbulence is not considered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stalling angle of attack is the angle at which we get maximum lift. Stalling angle is the maximum angle at which the aircraft can be maintained in a steady state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Total drag is the sum of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) lift dependent drag and lift independent drag",
            "b) lift dependent drag, lift independent drag and volume dependent wave drag",
            "c) lift dependent drag and volume dependent wave drag",
            "d) volume dependent wave drag and lift independent drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Total drag is the sum of lift dependent drag, lift independent drag and volume dependent wave drag. Also, in high subsonic mach number a value dependent wave drag is induced.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct relation between lift dependent drag, lift independent drag and drag coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CD=CDz+KCL2",
            "b) CD=CDz-KCL2",
            "c) CD=CDz*KCL2",
            "d) CD=CDz/KCL2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In high subsonic mach number a value dependent wave drag is induced. The components that act on the aircraft moving at high subsonic mach number are lift dependent drag, lift independent drag and volume dependent wave drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the two types of lift independent drag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) surface friction drag and profile drag",
            "b) induced drag and profile drag",
            "c) surface friction drag and induced drag",
            "d) parasitic drag and induced drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct relation between lift dependent drag, lift independent drag and drag coefficient is CD=CDz+KCL2 where CD is drag coefficient, CDz is lift independent drag, CL is lift independent drag and K is a constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "How is the zero-lift drag force related to atmospheric pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The zero-lift drag force is directly proportional to atmospheric pressure",
            "b) The zero-lift drag force is indirectly proportional to atmospheric pressure",
            "c) The zero-lift drag force is twice multiple to atmospheric pressure",
            "d)The zero-lift drag force is half divided to atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  There are three types of drag. They are parasitic drag which is further divided into form drag and skin friction drag. The second kind of drag is lift-induced drag and third type of drag is wave drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression for induced drag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V^2_e}\\) ",
            "b) YVe2",
            "c) \\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) ",
            "d) YVe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct expression for induced drag is \\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V^2_e}\\) where W is weight, V is velocity, Z is constant. Induced drag is the function of lift and caused when an aircraft is moving in the air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression for pressure drag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V^2_e}\\) ",
            "b) YVe2",
            "c) \\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) ",
            "d) YVe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct expression for pressure drag is YVe2 where Y is a constant and V is velocity. Pressure drag is caused due to the resultant pressure distribution over a surface of the body. It is generally occurred in turbulent flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D=YVee+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V^2_e}\\) ",
            "b) CD=CDz-KCL2",
            "c) D=Dz-Di",
            "d) Vemd=\\(\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct equation is D=YVee+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V^2_e}\\) where Y is a constant, V is velocity, W is weight, V is velocity, Z is constant and D is total drag. The total drag is the sum of pressure drag and induced drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct equation for minimum speed drag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vemd=\\(\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y}}\\) ",
            "b) Vemd=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y}}\\) ",
            "c) Vemd=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y^2}}\\) ",
            "d) Vemd=\\(\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y^2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct equation for minimum speed drag is Vemd=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y}}\\) where Y is a constant, V is velocity, W is weight, Y is a constant and Vemd is minimum speed drag. Induced drag is the function of lift and caused when an aircraft is moving in the air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "What is overall drag force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sum of drag force, zero-lift drag, lift-dependent drag and volume dependent wave drag",
            "b) The sum of lift-dependent drag and volume dependent wave drag",
            "c) The sum of drag force, lift-dependent drag and volume dependent wave drag",
            "d) The sum of drag force, zero-lift drag and lift-dependent drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum drag speed determines the best operating speeds of aircraft with thrust producing engines. The correct equation for minimum speed drag is Vemd=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y}}\\) where Y is a constant, V is velocity, W is weight, Y is a constant and Vemd is minimum speed drag. Induced drag is the function of lift and caused when an aircraft is moving in the air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct equation for the Prandtl-Glauert factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) β=\\(\\sqrt{1-M^2}\\) ",
            "b) β=\\(\\sqrt{1-M}\\) ",
            "c) β=\\(\\sqrt{M^2-1}\\) ",
            "d) β=\\(\\sqrt{1+M^2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lift-dependent drag is reduced with the reduction in total drag. Along with this the minimum air drag speed is also reduced. The total drag is the sum of pressure drag and induced drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Power is defined as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) product of force and acceleration",
            "b) ability to do work",
            "c) rate of doing work",
            "d) capacity to do work"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power is defined as rate of doing work. In another terms power can be defined as product of force and velocity. The standard S.I. unit of power is Watt. The other units are Watt, Kilowatt, Megawatt, Gigawatt, Horse power. 1 HP= 0.746 KW.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct relation between EAS and minimum power speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VemP=\\(\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{ZW^2}{3Y}}\\) ",
            "b) VemP=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW^2}{Y}}\\) ",
            "c) VemP=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW^2}{3Y}}\\) ",
            "d) VemP=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW}{3Y}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Drag power of an aircraft is achieved by multiplying drag force with true airspeed. The formula for drap power is given as P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=DVe=YVe3+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) where Y is a constant, Ve is velocity, W is weight, Z is constant and D is total drag and P is power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct relation between EAS and drag power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe3+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) ",
            "b) P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe3–\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) ",
            "c) P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe2-+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) ",
            "d) P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe2–\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct relation between EAS and minimum power speed is VemP=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW^2}{3Y}}\\) where Y is a constant, VemP is minimum power speed, W is weight, Z is constant. The true air speed have to be converted into equivalent airspeed before multiplication to derive the drag power equation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe3+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) ",
            "b) VemP=\\(\\sqrt[4]{\\frac{ZW}{3Y}}\\) ",
            "c) P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe2+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) ",
            "d) VemP=\\(\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{ZW^2}{3Y}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct relation between EAS and drag power is P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe3+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) where Y is a constant, Ve is velocity, W is weight, Z is constant and D is total drag and P is power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "The minimum drag speed and minimum power speed are related by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt[4]{3}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sqrt[4]{2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sqrt[2]{3}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sqrt[3]{3}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The true air speed have to be converted into equivalent airspeed before multiplication to derive the drag power equation. The equation of the drag power equation is P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe3+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) where Y is a constant, W is weight, Ve is velocity, Z is constant and D is total drag and P is power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "What is the relation between true air speed and equivalent air speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VT=\\(\\frac{V_e}{\\sqrt{\\sigma}}\\) ",
            "b) VT=\\(\\frac{V_e}{4\\sqrt{\\sigma}}\\) ",
            "c) Ve=\\(\\frac{V_T}{\\sqrt{\\sigma}}\\) ",
            "d) VT=\\(\\frac{V_e}{3\\sqrt{\\sigma}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct equation is P\\(\\sqrt{\\sigma}\\)=YVe3+\\(\\frac{ZW^2}{V_e}\\) where Y is a constant, W is weight, Ve is velocity, Z is constant and D is total drag and P is power.The true air speed have to be converted into equivalent airspeed before multiplication to derive the drag power equation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "The forms of powerplant used in aircraft propulsion are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thrust-producing and power producing",
            "b) weight-producing and power producing",
            "c) thrust-producing and weight producing",
            "d) thrust-producing, power producing and weight producing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two forms of powerplant used in aircraft propulsion are thrust-producing and power producing. Thrust-producing engines include turbojet, turbofan and rocket while power producing engines are get engine and piston engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "What is thrust producing powerplant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propulsive force that is directed by increasing momentum of the airflow",
            "b) Propulsive force that is obtained from shaft power by propeller",
            "c) Propulsive force that is directed by decreasing momentum of the airflow",
            "d) Propulsive force that is obtained from engine power by propeller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two forms of powerplant used in aircraft propulsion are thrust-producing and power producing. A thrust-producing powerplant is the one whose propulsive force is obtained by increasing momentum of the airflow through the engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a thrust-producing powerplant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) turbojet",
            "b) turbofan",
            "c) rocket",
            "d) piston engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The two forms of powerplant used in aircraft propulsion are thrust-producing and power producing. A thrust-producing powerplant is the one whose propulsive force is obtained by increasing momentum of the airflow through the engine. Examples of thrust-producing powerplant are turbojet, turbofan and rocket.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "What is the function of the compressor in an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To supply sufficient amount of air for combustion",
            "b) Increase velocity",
            "c) Decrease pressure",
            "d) To cut off the air flow inside the aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The high-energy air is expelled from the nozzle of an aircraft with increased momentum to produce thrust to the aircraft. This process is occurred in the thrust-producing powerplant. Some examples of thrust-producing powerplant are turbojet, turbofan and rocket.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "What is net propulsive force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The stream force exited at the exit of the engine",
            "b) The difference between the stream force entering and leaving the engine",
            "c) The stream force entering at the entrance of the engine",
            "d) The product of stream force entering and leaving the engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The function of the compressor in an aircraft to supply sufficient amount of air for combustion. In a compressor the velocity may increase or decrease accordingly but the pressure increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "What is gross thrust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust produced at the exit of the nozzle",
            "b) The difference between the stream force entering and leaving the engine",
            "c) The stream force exited at the exit of the engine",
            "d) The product of stream force entering and leaving the engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The net propulsive force is the difference between the stream force entering and leaving the engine. It is represented by FN. The thrust produced by an aircraft is depended on the net propulsive force.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The net propulsive thrust is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FN=FG-Dm",
            "b) FN=FG+Dm",
            "c) FN=FG*Dm",
            "d) FN=FG/Dm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gross thrust is the thrust produced at the exit of the nozzle. It is represented by FG. It is also equal to the rate of change of momentum at the exhaust gas flow. The equation is given as FG=ṁVj where FG is gross thrust, ṁ is mass flow rate and Vj is exit velocity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What kind of forces is responsible for airframe drag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forces resulting from external flow",
            "b) Forces resulting from internal flow",
            "c) Forces resulting from discontinuous flow",
            "d) Forces resulting from continuous flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flow due to intake flow is known as momentum drag. It is the rate of change of momentum in the intake flow. It is represented by Dm. The equation is Dm=ṁV where Dm is momentum drag, ṁ is mass flow rate and V is air intake flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "What is thrust drag accounting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allocation of flow forces to the airframe drag",
            "b) Allocation of flow forces to the wave drag",
            "c) Allocation of flow forces to the induced drag",
            "d) Allocation of flow forces to the parasitic drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The allocation of flow forces to the airframe drag or to the propulsive thrust is known as the thrust drag. It is important to distinguish these force contributions else there results a wrong estimation of the aircraft performance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "The net thrust of the powerplant is affected by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pressure and temperature",
            "b) altitude andtemperature",
            "c) temperature and mach number",
            "d) mach number and altitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The net thrust of the powerplant is affected by mach number and altitude. As it is not possible to postulate precise function that will relate thrust and mach number and altitude, we develop simple relations that give us the characteristic variation of thrust along with the changes in mach number and altitude.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct equation for net thrust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FN=ṁ(Vj+V)",
            "b) FN=(Vj-V)",
            "c) FN=ṁ(Vj-V)",
            "d) FN=ṁ(V-Vj)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The equation for net thrust is given by FN=ṁ(Vj-V) where FN is net thrust, ṁ is mass flow rate, Vj is exit velocity and V is inlet velocity. In other words the net propulsive force is the difference between the stream force entering and leaving the engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "What is the net thrust of the jet engine if the mass flow rate is 500kg/s, exit velocity is 1000m/s and inlet velocity is 600m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400kN",
            "b) 600kN",
            "c) 500kN",
            "d) 200kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The answer is 200Kn. Given ṁ=500kg/s, Vj=1000m/s and V=600m/s. Substitute the values in the formula, FN=ṁ(Vj-V).\nOn substituting FN=500 (1000– 600)\nOn solving FN=20000N.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "How is thrust related to altitude of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust is directly proportional",
            "b) Thrust is indirectly proportional",
            "c) They are independent of each other",
            "d) Thrust increases square of altitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relation between altitude of an aircraft and thrust is that the thrust is indirectly proportional to the altitude of an aircraft i.e. thrust decreases as there is an increase in the altitude, similarly the thrust increases as there is decrease in the altitude.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "What will be the net thrust when momentum drag is 50N and gross thrust is 400N?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 450N",
            "b) 8N",
            "c) 350N",
            "d) 350kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of the engine exhaust flow is a function of the temperature of the exhaust gas and this can be determined by the throttle setting. For any given engine thrust setting the exhaust gas velocity can be considered constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "What is power producing powerplant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propulsive force that is directed by increasing momentum of the airflow",
            "b) Propulsive force that is obtained from shaft power by propeller",
            "c) Propulsive force that is directed by decreasing momentum of the airflow",
            "d) Propulsive force that is obtained from engine power by propeller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two forms of powerplant used in aircraft propulsion are thrust-producing and power producing. A power-producing powerplant is the one whose propulsive force is obtained from shaft power by propeller.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a power-producing powerplant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbojet",
            "b) Turbofan",
            "c) Rocket",
            "d) Piston engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The two forms of powerplant used in aircraft propulsion are thrust-producing and power producing. A thrust-producing powerplant is the one whose propulsive force is obtained by increasing momentum of the airflow through the engine. A power-producing powerplant is the one whose propulsive force is obtained from shaft power by propeller. Examples of thrust-producing powerplant are turbojet, turbofan and rocket. Examples of power-producing powerplant are gas turbine and piston engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust power delivered by an aircraft engine is always less than shaft power delivered",
            "b) Thrust power delivered by an aircraft engine is always more than shaft power delivered",
            "c) Thrust power delivered by an aircraft engine is directly proportional to shaft power delivered",
            "d) Thrust power delivered by an aircraft engine is inversly proportional to shaft power delivered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The thrust power delivered by an aircraft engine is always less than shaft power delivered. This is because in a power-producing engine the shaft power have to be converted into thrust during which there occur losses and hence the thrust power delivered by an aircraft engine is always less than shaft power delivered.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents the correct formula for propeller efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) η=\\(\\frac{T}{P}\\) ",
            "b) η=\\(\\frac{P}{TV}\\) ",
            "c) η=\\(\\frac{T}{PV}\\) ",
            "d) η=\\(\\frac{TV}{P}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct formula for propeller efficiency is η=\\(\\frac{TV}{P}\\) where η is propeller efficiency T is thrust and V is true airspeed and P is shaft power. The propeller efficiency is the ratio of thrust-power output by the shaft power input of a powerplant engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Which of the following relations are correct for pressure coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CP=\\(\\frac{P}{\\frac{\\rho n^3D^4}{2}}\\) ",
            "b) CP=\\(\\frac{P}{\\frac{\\rho n^2D^5}{2}}\\) ",
            "c) CP=\\(\\frac{TV}{\\frac{\\rho n^3D^5}{2}}\\) ",
            "d) CP=\\(\\frac{P}{\\frac{\\rho n^3D^5}{2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The propeller efficiency depends on the propeller advance ratio and power coefficient. Propeller advance ratio is given by J=\\(\\frac{V}{nD}\\) where J is propeller advance ratio, V is true airspeed, n is rotational speed and D is propeller diameter. Also the pressure coefficient is given by CP=\\(\\frac{P}{\\frac{\\rho n^3D^5}{2}}\\) where CP is pressure coefficient, ρ is density, P is shaft power, n is rotational speed and D is propeller diameter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following relations are correct for propeller advance ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) J=\\(\\frac{TV}{nD}\\) ",
            "b) J=\\(\\frac{P}{nD}\\) ",
            "c) J=\\(\\frac{V}{nD}\\) ",
            "d) J=\\(\\frac{PV}{nD}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The propeller efficiency depends on the propeller advance ratio and power coefficient. The pressure coefficient is given by CP=\\(\\frac{P}{\\frac{\\rho n^3D^5}{2}}\\) where CP is pressure coefficient, ρ is density, P is shaft power, n is rotational speed and D is propeller diameter. Also propeller advance ratio is given by J= \\(\\frac{V}{nD}\\) where J is propeller advance ratio, V is true airspeed, n is rotational speed and D is propeller diameter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "What is the propeller advance ratio for the power-producing powerplant when the true airspeed is 300m/s and the diameter of propeller is 0.5 m with rotational speed of 117.81rad/sec?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.01",
            "b) 9.02",
            "c) 5.09",
            "d) 5.89"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The propeller efficiency depends on the propeller advance ratio and power coefficient. Propeller advance ratio is given by J=\\(\\frac{V}{nD}\\) where J is propeller advance ratio, V is true airspeed, n is rotational speed and D is propeller diameter. Also the pressure coefficient is given by CP=\\(\\frac{P}{\\frac{\\rho n^3D^5}{2}}\\) where CP is pressure coefficient, ρ is density, P is shaft power, n is rotational speed and D is propeller diameter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "What is meant by static thrust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) thrust at maximum airspeed",
            "b) power at zero airspeed",
            "c) thrust at zero airspeed",
            "d) power at maximum airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The answer is 5.09 radian. Given advance ratio V=300m/s , n=117.81rad/sec, D=0.5 m. From the equation J=\\(\\frac{V}{nD}\\) we can find propeller advance ratio. Substitute the given values in the equation J=\\(\\frac{300}{117.81*0.5}\\) \nOn solving J=5.09 radian.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct equation for longitudinal performance equation of motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{\\eta P}{V}\\)=D-Wsinγ2+mV",
            "b) \\(\\frac{\\eta P}{V}\\)=D+Wsinγ2-mV",
            "c) \\(\\frac{\\eta T}{V}\\)=D+Wsinγ2+mV",
            "d) \\(\\frac{\\eta P}{V}\\)=D+Wsinγ2+mV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Static thrust is the thrust at that is produced at zero airspeed. This static thrust decreases with the increase in airspeed of a power-producing engine. This condition arises when propulsive increases with decrease in airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "The minimum drag speed is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{4}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\gamma \\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{4}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\gamma \\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct formula for minimum drag speed is given by \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{4}\\) where W is weight, ρ is density, K is constant, S is span area and CDz is coefficient of lift dependent drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "The minimum drag mach number is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{4}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\gamma \\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{4}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\gamma \\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct formula for minimum drag mach number is given by \\(\\big(\\frac{2W}{\\gamma \\rho S}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\big(\\frac{K}{C_{Dz}}\\big)^\\frac{1}{4}\\) where W is weight, ρ is density, K is constant, S is span area, γ is ratio of specific heats and CDz is coefficient of lift dependent drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "At steady state flight condition",
        "Options": [
            "a) T>D",
            "b) T<D",
            "c) T=D",
            "d) T≠D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At steady state flight condition the thrust produced by the aircraft is same as the drag produced by the aircraft i.e. T=D. At this state the minimum power speed is given by \\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[4]{3}}\\)=Vmd where Vmd is minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct relation between minimum power speed and minimum drag speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vmp=\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[2]{3}}\\)Vmd",
            "b) Vmp=\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[4]{3}}\\)Vmd",
            "c) Vmp=\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[3]{3}}\\)Vmd",
            "d) Vmp=\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[4]{5}}\\)Vmd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At steady state flight condition the thrust produced by the aircraft is same as the drag produced by the aircraft i.e. T=D. The relation between minimum drag speed and minimum power speed is given by Vmp=\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[4]{3}}\\)Vmd where Vmd is minimum drag speed and Vmp is minimum power speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "What is the value of minimum power speed when minimum drag speed is 300m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 173.21 m/s",
            "b) 227.95 m/s",
            "c) 134.16 m/s",
            "d) 200.62 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct answer is 227.95 m/s. Given Vmd is 300m/s. From the formula Vmp=\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[4]{3}}\\)Vmd substitute the values.\nOn substituting we get, Vmp=\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt[4]{3}}\\)*300\nVmp=227.95m/s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "What is the relative airspeed of an aircraft whose airspeed and minimum drag speed are 500m/s and 150m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.33",
            "b) 0.3",
            "c) 33.33",
            "d) 0.333"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Airspeed with minimum power relates to the performance of the aircraft with power producing engine whereas minimum drag speed relates to the performance of aircraft with thrust-producing engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "What will be the drag to minimum drag ratio when the relative airspeed is 3.33?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.49",
            "b) 1.51",
            "c) 5.59",
            "d) 1.82"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Airspeed with minimum power relates to the performance of the aircraft with power producing engine whereas minimum drag speed relates to the performance of aircraft with thrust-producing engine. In a glider the engine uses both minimum power speed and minimum drag speed but does not have any engine present.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct performance equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}+τ\\big]+\\frac{1}{2}\\big[u^2+\\frac{1}{u^2}\\big]\\)=Emax\\(\\big\\{sin\\gamma_2-\\frac{V}{g}\\big\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}+τ\\big]-\\frac{1}{2}\\big[u^2+\\frac{1}{u^2}\\big]\\)=Emax\\(\\big\\{sin\\gamma_2-\\frac{V}{g}\\big\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}+τ\\big]+\\frac{1}{2}\\big[u^2+\\frac{1}{u^2}\\big]\\)=Emax\\(\\big\\{sin\\gamma_2+\\frac{V}{g}\\big\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}+τ\\big]-\\frac{1}{2}\\big[u^2+\\frac{1}{u^2}\\big]\\)=Emax\\(\\big\\{sin\\gamma_2+\\frac{V}{g}\\big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The answer is 3.33. Given, airspeed is 500m/s and minimum drag speed is 150m/s. From the formula u=\\(\\frac{V}{V_{md}}\\) where V is airspeed and Vmd is minimum drag speed. On substituting the values we get u= \\(\\frac{500}{150}\\) \nu=3.33.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "What is a trim in aircraft performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The state of equilibrium where the forces and moments are balanced",
            "b) The state of equilibrium where the forces and moments are not balanced",
            "c) The state of equilibrium where only the forces are balanced",
            "d) The state of equilibrium where only the moments are balanced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cruise performance the aircraft is considered to be steady, level, straight, symmetric flight with no acceleration or maneuver.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "An aircraft is climbing with a 20° of climb angle and a 5° of angle of attack having a mass of 11,000 kg and aircraft drag is 9,000 N then determine engine thrust.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5257.79 N",
            "b) 1810.97 N",
            "c) 28013.99 N",
            "d) 46082.75 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Trim is a state of equilibrium where the forces and moments are balanced. In this condition \n\nFN=D\nL = W\n\nWhere FN is normal force acting on the aircraft, D is drag, L is lift and W is weight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "An aircraft is climbing with a 20° of climb angle and a 5° of angle of attack having a mass of 11,000 kg and aircraft drag is 9,000 N then determine aircraft lift.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11453.17 N",
            "b) 9220.07 N",
            "c) 11553.17 N",
            "d) 97385.85 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aircraft weight=mg=11000*9.81=107910 N.\nEngine thrust: From equating the horizontal forces we get the following equation: T cos α=D+Wsin γ\nT=\\(\\frac{D+Wsin\\gamma}{cos\\alpha}\\)=\\(\\frac{9000+107910*sin(20)}{cos(5)}\\) \nT=46082.75 N.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "An aircraft is climbing with a 20° of climb angle and a 5° of angle of attack having a mass of 11,000 kg and aircraft thrust is 46082.75N then determine aircraft drag.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 33898.64 N",
            "b) 52708.59 N",
            "c) 82814.78 N",
            "d) 8999.99 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aircraft weight=mg=11000*9.81=107910 N.\nEngine thrust: From equating the forces we get the following equation: T cos α= D+W sin γ\nT=\\(\\frac{D+Wsin\\gamma}{cos\\alpha}\\)=\\(\\frac{9000+107910*sin(20)}{cos(5)}\\) \nT=46082.75 N.\nFrom equating the vertical forces we get the following equation: L+Tsinα=Wcosγ\nL=107910*cos(20)–46082.75*sin(5)\nL=97385.85 N.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "What is specific air range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal distance flown per unit of fuel consumed",
            "b) vertical distance flown per unit of fuel consumed",
            "c) horizontal distance flown per unit time",
            "d) vertical distance flown per unit time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aircraft weight=mg=11000*9.81=107910 N.\nEngine thrust: From equating the horizontal forces we get the following equation: Tcosα=D+Wsinγ\nD=Tcosα-Wsinγ\nD=46082.75*cos(5)–107910*sin(20)\nD=8999.99 N.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "What is specific endurance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is instantaneous flight distance per unit of time",
            "b) It is instantaneous flight time per unit of distance",
            "c) It is instantaneous flight distance per unit of fuel consumed",
            "d) It is instantaneous flight time per unit of fuel consumed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific air range (SAR) is the horizontal distance flown per unit of fuel consumed. It can be expressed as SAR=\\(\\frac{V}{Q_f}\\) where V is true airspeed and Qf is fuel mass flow. The units of SAR are length/mass i.e. nm/Kg.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "What will be the specific endurance of an aircraft having fuel mass flow 0.75 kg/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.33 s/kg",
            "b) 3.33 s/kg",
            "c) 1.33 s/kg",
            "d) 2.33 s/kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Specific endurance (SE) is the instantaneous flight time per unit of fuel consumed. Specific endurance (SE) can be expressed as SE=\\(\\frac{1}{Q_f}\\) where Qf is fuel mass flow. The units of SAR are time/mass i.e. hr/Kg.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "What will be the specific endurance of an aircraft having fuel mass flow 0.75 kg/s and true air speed is 300m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 m/kg",
            "b) 333 m/kg",
            "c) 133 m/kg",
            "d) 250 m/kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In cruise performance the fuel mass flow determines the rate of change of mass of the aircraft. It is expressed by the formula Qf=\\(\\frac{-dm}{dt}\\) where dm is mass rate and dt is time rate. The fuel mass is always negative as mass of the aircraft always decreases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "What is specific fuel consumption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the fuel flow rate per unit distance",
            "b) It is the fuel flow rate per unit thrust",
            "c) It is the fuel flow rate per unit time",
            "d) It is the mass flow rate per unit thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific thrust is defined as the fuel flow rate per unit thrust produced by the aircraft. The units of specific thrust are kg/N hr. The expression for specific fuel consumption is given by C=\\(\\frac{Q_f}{F_N}\\) where Qf is fuel mass flow and FN is thrust produced by the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "There are ___________ fuel flow laws.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) three",
            "d) four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three fuel flow laws. They are:\ni. C=C1, here specific fuel consumption is constant\nii. C=C2θ1/2Mn , here it considers temperature and effects of mach number\niii. C=C3+C4M and C=C5+C6FN, here the assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "What is the significance of first fuel flow law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific fuel consumption is not considered",
            "b) Considers temperature and effects of mach number",
            "c) Assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data",
            "d) Specific fuel consumption is constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The significance of first fuel flow law is that the specific fuel consumption is constant. The significance of second fuel flow law is that it considers temperature and effects of mach number. The significance of third fuel flow law is that assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "What is the significance of second fuel flow law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) specific fuel consumption is not considered",
            "b) considers temperature and effects of mach number",
            "c) assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data",
            "d) specific fuel consumption is constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The significance of first fuel flow law is that the specific fuel consumption is constant. The significance of second fuel flow law is that it considers temperature and effects of mach number. The significance of third fuel flow law is that assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "What is the significance of third fuel flow law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific fuel consumption is not considered",
            "b) Considers temperature and effects of mach number",
            "c) Assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data",
            "d) Specific fuel consumption is constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The significance of first fuel flow law is that the specific fuel consumption is constant. The significance of second fuel flow law is that it considers temperature and effects of mach number. The significance of third fuel flow law is that assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "What is meant by fuel ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ratio of initial fuel of aircraft to that of final weight of aircraft",
            "b) ratio of final fuel of aircraft to that of initial weight of aircraft",
            "c) ratio of initial weight of aircraft to that of final weight of aircraft",
            "d) ratio of final weight of aircraft to that of initial weight of aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The significance of first fuel flow law is that the specific fuel consumption is constant. The significance of second fuel flow law is that it considers temperature and effects of mach number. The significance of third fuel flow law is that assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data. The second fuel flow law is used in the turbojet or turbofan. Also it takes in account the temperature and effects of mach number.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SAR=\\(\\frac{C}{V}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) ",
            "b) SE=\\(\\frac{C}{V}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) ",
            "c) SAR=\\(\\frac{V}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) ",
            "d) SAR=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The fuel ratio is the ratio of initial weight of aircraft to that of final weight of aircraft. It is denoted by ω. The equation is given by ω=\\(\\frac{W_i}{W_f}\\) where Wi is initial weight of aircraft and Wf is final weight of aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "There are two fuel flow laws. They are:",
        "Options": [
            "i.\tC=C1, here specific fuel consumption is constant",
            "ii.\t C=C3+C4M, here it considers temperature and effects of mach number",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The equation for specific air range is given by SAR=\\(\\frac{V}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, W is weight. The significance of first fuel flow law is that the specific fuel consumption is constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "What is the fuel ratio of aircraft when initial and final weight are 385560kg and 15560kg?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34.78",
            "b) 24.78",
            "c) 56.76",
            "d) 45.65"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are three fuel flow laws. They are:\ni.\tC=C1, here specific fuel consumption is constant\nii.\tC=C2θ1/2Mn , here it considers temperature and effects of mach number\niii.\tC=C3+C4M and C=C5+C6FN, here the assumptions are taken for empirical fuel flow data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "What is the condition of cruise method 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air pressure is increased",
            "b) Aircraft weight is increased",
            "c) W/D ratio is kept constant",
            "d) L/D ratio is varying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cruise method 1 the air pressure is decreased as well as the aircraft weight is decreased. In cruise method 1 the W/p ratio is maintained constant and also L/D ratio is also kept constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Cruise climb technique is involved in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cruise method 1",
            "b) cruise method 2",
            "c) cruise method 3",
            "d) cruise method 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In cruise method 1 the air pressure is decreased as well as the aircraft weight is decreased. In cruise method 1 the W/p ratio is maintained constant and also L/D ratio is also kept constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement regarding cruise method 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) W/D ratio is kept constant",
            "b) L/D ratio is varying",
            "c) Air pressure is decreased",
            "d) Aircraft weight is decreased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cruise climb technique is involved in cruise method 1. In cruise method 1 the air pressure is decreased as well as the aircraft weight is decreased. In cruise method 1 the W/p ratio is maintained constant and also L/D ratio is also kept constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "What is Brequet Range expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R1 = \\(\\frac{D}{C}\\frac{L}{V}\\) ln ω",
            "b) R1 = \\(\\frac{1}{C} \\left[\\frac{2W}{\\rho S}\\right]^{\\frac{1}{2}} \\frac{C_L^{\\frac{1}{2}}}{C_D}\\) ln ω",
            "c) R1 = \\(\\frac{1}{V} \\left[\\frac{2W}{\\rho S}\\right]^{\\frac{1}{2}} \\frac{C_L^{\\frac{1}{2}}}{C_D}\\)  ln ω",
            "d) R1 = \\(\\frac{V}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\) ln ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In cruise method 1 the air pressure is decreased as well as the aircraft weight is decreased. In cruise method 1 the W/p ratio is maintained constant and also L/D ratio is also kept constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Brequet Range expression value is maximum at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.316 Vmd",
            "b) 1.216 Vmd",
            "c) 1.3 Vmd",
            "d) 1.2 Vmd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Brequet Range expression is given by R1 = \\(\\frac{V}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\) ln ω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, and ω is fuel ratio. This Brequet Range expression comes in the cruise method 1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "What is range factor in cruise method 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\left[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C} E_{max}\\right]\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\left[\\frac{V_{max}}{C} E_{max}\\right]\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^4}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Brequet Range expression is given by R1 = \\(\\frac{V}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\) ln ω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, and ω is fuel ratio. This Brequet Range expression comes in the cruise method 1. Brequet Range expression value is maximum at 1.316 Vmd.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following does range factor consists?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air density",
            "b) Cruise weight",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Cruise weight and air density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Range factor in cruise method 1 is given by \\(\\left[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C} E_{max}\\right]\\). The range equation in cruise method 1 is given by R1 = \\(\\left[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C} E_{max}\\right]\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\) ln ω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, Emax is endurance and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents range function?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\)lnω",
            "b) \\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{max}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\)lnω",
            "c) \\(\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\)lnω",
            "d) \\(\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^4}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\)lnω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Relative airspeed acts as a shaping factor. Relative airspeed is given by \\(\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\) where u is relative airspeed. The range equation in cruise method 1 is given by R1=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\)lnω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, Emax is endurance, u is relative airspeed and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct statement regarding cruise method 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel ratio for very long range aircraft is 1.3",
            "b) Fuel ratio for short range aircraft is 1.3",
            "c) Fuel ratio for medium to long range aircraft is 1.3",
            "d) Fuel ratio for short range aircraft is 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The range function is given by \\(\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\)lnω. The range equation in cruise method 1 is given by R1=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\)lnω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, Emax is endurance, u is relative airspeed and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What is endurance factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\big[\\frac{E_{max}}{C}\\big]\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\big[\\frac{E_{max}}{VC}\\big]\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\big\\{\\frac{2u^4}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maximum range is given when the aircraft is fly’s at u=1.316. The range equation in cruise method 1 is given by R1=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}\\)lnω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, Emax is endurance, u is relative airspeed and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "What is endurance function?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\big[\\frac{E_{max}}{C}\\big]\\) ",
            "b) lnω",
            "c) \\(\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fuel ratio for medium to long range aircraft is 1.3 and for short range aircraft is 1.1 and very long range aircraft is 1.5. Fuel ratio is given by ω. Fuel ratio is given by ratio of initial weight of aircraft to that of final weight of aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which factor must be reduced in constant angle of attack and constant altitude method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach number",
            "b) Angle of attack",
            "c) Altitude",
            "d) Temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The factor that must be reduced in cruise method 2 (also known as constant angle of attack and constant altitude method) is mach number. Also the ratio of lift to drag and relative airspeed are kept constant i.e. L/D ratio and uare constant throughout the method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following indicates the range formula in cruise method 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\big(\\frac{2}{\\rho SC_L}\\big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\int_{W_{i}}^{W_{f}}\\frac{dW}{W^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\) ",
            "b) R=\\(\\Big(\\frac{2}{\\rho SC_L}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{L}{D}\\int_{W_{i}}^{W_{f}}\\frac{dW}{W^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\) ",
            "c) R=\\(\\Big(\\frac{2}{\\rho SC_L}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{LC}{D}\\int_{W_{i}}^{W_{f}}\\frac{dW}{W^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\) ",
            "d) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2}{\\rho SC_L}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{L}{D}\\int_{W_{i}}^{W_{f}}\\frac{dW}{W^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct range equation of cruise method 2 is given by R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2}{\\rho SC_L}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{L}{D}\\int_{W_{i}}^{W_{f}}\\frac{dW}{W^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\) where R is range of the cruise, C is specific fuel consumption, S is span, ρ is density, CL is coefficient of lift, L/D is lift to drag ratio, Wf and Wi are final and initial weights.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct integrated range equation of cruise method 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2W_i}{S_{\\rho}}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{C_L}{C_D}2\\Big(1-\\omega^{\\frac{-1}{2}}\\Big)\\) ",
            "b) R=\\(\\Big(\\frac{2W_i}{S_{\\rho}}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{C_{L}^{0.5}}{C_D}2\\Big(1-\\omega^{\\frac{-1}{2}}\\Big)\\) ",
            "c) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2W_i}{S_{\\rho}}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{C_{L}^{0.5}}{C_D}2\\Big(1-\\omega^{\\frac{-1}{2}}\\Big)\\) ",
            "d) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2W_i}{S_{\\rho}}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{C_{L}^{0.5}}{C_D}2\\Big(1-\\omega\\Big)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct equation of cruise method 2 is R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2W_i}{S_{\\rho}}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{C_{L}^{0.5}}{C_D}2\\Big(1-\\omega^{\\frac{-1}{2}}\\Big)\\) where R is range of the cruise, C is specific fuel consumption, S is span, ρ is density, CL is coefficient of lift, Cl/Cd is ratio of coefficient of lift to drag, Wi is initial weight and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Cruise method 2 is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant angle of attack and variable mach number",
            "b) constant angle of attack and constant mach number",
            "c) constant angle of attack and constant altitude number",
            "d) constant mach number and constant altitude number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cruise method 2 also known as constant angle of attack and constant altitude method. In cruise method 2 altitude, the ratio of lift to drag and relative airspeed are kept constant i.e. L/D ratio and u and h are constant throughout the method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors are not constant in cruise method 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) altitude",
            "b) relative airspeed",
            "c) mach number",
            "d) angle of attack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cruise method 2 also known as constant angle of attack and constant altitude method. In cruise method 2 altitude, the ratio of lift to drag and relative airspeed are kept constant i.e. L/D ratio and u and h are constant throughout the method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a reason of disadvantage of cruise method 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased mach number",
            "b) Fuel saving",
            "c) Increased time of flight",
            "d) Increased weight of aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In cruise method 2 the range factor is given by R=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}2\\Big(1-\\omega^{\\frac{-1}{2}}\\Big)\\) where \\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\) is range factor and is same of that in cruise method 1 but overall range of cruise method 2 is less than that of cruise method 1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases cruise method 2 is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Commercial aircraft",
            "b) Fighter aircraft",
            "c) Military",
            "d) Patrol and surveillance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The endurance of cruise method 2 is identical to that of cruise method 1. E=\\(\\Big[\\frac{E_{max}}{C}\\Big]\\Big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\Big\\}l_n\\omega\\) where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, Emax is endurance, u is relative airspeed and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Which factor must be reduced in cruise method 3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach number",
            "b) Angle of attack",
            "c) Altitude",
            "d) Temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The factor that must be reduced in cruise method 3 (also known as constant mach number and constant altitude method) is angle of attack. Also the ratio of weight to lift coefficient and relative airspeed are kept constant i.e. W/CL ratio and u are constant throughout the method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Which of the following indicates the range formula in cruise method 3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2}{\\rho SC_L}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\int_{W_i}^{W_f}\\frac{dW}{W^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\) ",
            "b) R=\\(\\Big(\\frac{2}{\\rho SC_L}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{L}{D}\\int_{W_i}^{W_f}\\frac{dW}{W^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\) ",
            "c) R=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]2u_i\\Big\\{tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{u_{i}^2}\\Big]+tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{\\omega u_{i}^2}\\Big]\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "d) R=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]2u_i\\Big\\{tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{u_{i}^2}\\Big]-tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{\\omega u_{i}^2}\\Big]\\Big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct equation of cruise method 3 is R=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]2u_i\\Big\\{tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{u_{i}^2}\\Big]-tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{\\omega u_{i}^2}\\Big]\\Big\\}\\) where R is range of the cruise, C is specific fuel consumption, Emax is endurance, Vmdi is relative airspeed and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct integrated range equation of cruise method 3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2W_i}{S\\rho}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{C_L}{C_D}2\\Big(1-\\omega^{\\frac{-1}{2}}\\Big)\\) ",
            "b) R=\\(\\frac{V}{C}\\int_{W_i}^{W_f}\\frac{dW}{D}\\) ",
            "c) R=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]2u_i\\Big\\{tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{u_{i}^2}\\Big]-tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{\\omega u_{i}^2}\\Big]\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "d) R=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\Big(\\frac{2W_i}{S\\rho}\\Big)^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\frac{C_{L}^{0.5}}{C_D}2\\Big(1-\\omega^{\\frac{-1}{2}}\\Big)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct equation of cruise method 3 is R=\\(\\frac{V}{C}\\int_{W_i}^{W_f}\\frac{dW}{D}\\) where R is range, V is velocity, C is specific fuel consumption, D drag and Wf, Wiare final and initial weights.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Cruise method 3 is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant angle of attack and variable mach number",
            "b) constant angle of attack and constant mach number",
            "c) constant angle of attack and constant altitude number",
            "d) constant mach number and constant altitude number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cruise method 3 also known as constant altitude and constant mach number method. In cruise method 3 altitude, mach number and relative airspeed are kept constant i.e. M, u and h are constant throughout the method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Which factor is not a constant factor in cruise method 3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach number",
            "b) Angle of attack",
            "c) Altitude",
            "d) Relative air speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factor that must be reduced in cruise method 3 (also known as constant angle of attack and constant altitude method) is angle of attack. Also the ratio of weight to lift coefficient and relative airspeed are kept constant i.e. W/CL ratio and u are constant throughout the method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a reason of disadvantage of cruise method 3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased mach number",
            "b) Fuel saving",
            "c) Increased time of flight",
            "d) Increased weight of aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In cruise method 3 the range factor is given by R=\\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]2u_i\\Big\\{tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{u_{i}^2}\\Big]-tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{\\omega u_{i}^2}\\Big]\\Big\\}\\) where \\(\\Big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C}E_{max}\\Big]\\) is range factor and range pf aircraft is function of the range factor of the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases cruise method 3 is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Commercial aircraft",
            "b) Fighter aircraft",
            "c) Military",
            "d) Patrol and surveillance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The endurance of cruise method 3 is not identical to that of cruise method 1. E=\\(\\Big[\\frac{E_{max}}{C}\\Big]2\\Big\\{tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{u_{i}^2}\\Big]-tan^{-1}\\Big[\\frac{1}{\\omega u_{i}^2}\\Big]\\Big\\}\\)where where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, Emax is endurance, u is relative airspeed and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "The range and endurance are proportional to which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fuel flow",
            "b) net thrust",
            "c) bypass ratio",
            "d) airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The range and endurance are proportional only to net thrust. The fuel flow laws proved to be a constant idealized laws. Though fuel flow laws cannot describe all the characteristics of the engine they are proved to be a constant idealized laws.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a correct form of fuel flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C=C2θMn",
            "b) C=C2θ\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)M",
            "c) C=C2θM",
            "d) C=C2θ\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)Mn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct formula for fuel flow is C=C2θ\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)Mn where θ is the temperature, M is mach number and n varies from 0.2-0.6 for turbojet to turbofan. It depends on the bypass ratio of the combustion chamber.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "The formula for velocity of maximum specific air range is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\big[\\frac{3-n}{1+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\big[\\frac{3-n}{1+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{3}}\\)Vmd",
            "c) \\(\\big[\\frac{3-n}{1+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd",
            "d) \\(\\big[\\frac{3+n}{1+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thrust produced is the functional form of engine speed and flight Mach number. The temperature decreases as the altitude increases so that during the cruise-climb situation the rotational speed increases and mach number increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "The formula for velocity of maximum specific endurance is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\big[\\frac{3+n}{1+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd",
            "b) \\(\\big[\\frac{2+n}{1+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd",
            "c) \\(\\big[\\frac{2+n}{2-n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd",
            "d) \\(\\big[\\frac{2-n}{2+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct formula for fuel flow is C=C2\\(\\theta^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\)Mn where θ is the temperature, M is mach number and n varies from 0.2-0.6 for turbojet to turbofan. It depends on the bypass ratio of the combustion chamber.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "What is the velocity of maximum specific air range of the engine when the maximum air speed is 400m/s and the exponential value is 0.2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300.84",
            "b) 380.43",
            "c) 440.76",
            "d) 494.37"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct formula for fuel flow is C=C2\\(\\theta^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\)Mn where θ is the temperature, M is mach number and n varies from 0.2-0.6 for turbojet to turbofan. It depends on the bypass ratio of the combustion chamber.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "What is the velocity of maximum specific endurance of the engine when the maximum air speed is 400m/s and the exponential value is 0.2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 350.43",
            "b) 490.34",
            "c) 494.37",
            "d) 380.43"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula for velocity of maximum specific air range is  \\(\\big[\\frac{3-n}{1+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd where ‘n’ is the exponent and Vmd is maximum velocity. The value of ‘n’ depends on the value of bypass ratio of the engine. This implies that as the value of ‘n’ increases the bypass ratio increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "What is the value of ‘n’ exponential in the fuel flow law for a high bypass ratio turbofan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 0.6",
            "d) 0.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The formula forvelocity of maximum specific endurance is \\(\\big[\\frac{2-n}{2+n}\\big]^{\\frac{1}{4}}\\)Vmd where ‘n’ is the exponent and Vmd is maximum velocity. The value of ‘n’ depends on the value of bypass ratio of the engine. This implies that as the value of ‘n’ increases the bypass ratio increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a correct statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in initial weight of aircraft implies increase in fuel available for cruise",
            "b) Decrease in initial weight of aircraft implies increase in fuel available for cruise",
            "c) Increase in initial weight of aircraft implies decrease in fuel available for cruise",
            "d) Increase in initial weight of aircraft does not have any effect on the fuel available for cruise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range factor is proportional to the square root of the initial cruising weight. This way we know that the range of the aircraft will increase with its weight. This implies that increase in weight increases the fuel availability for the cruise.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "What happens if the final fuel weight increases in an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel ratio increases",
            "b) Fuel ratio is not effected",
            "c) Range of the aircraft is increased",
            "d) Range of the aircraft is decreased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Increase in initial weight of aircraft implies increase in fuel available for cruise. The increase in initial weight increases the range of the aircraft which results in increasing the aircraft efficiency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "What is the relation between air temperature and the aircraft range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air temperature increases with increase in the aircraft range",
            "b) Air temperature decreases with increase in the aircraft range",
            "c) Air temperature increases with decrease in the aircraft range",
            "d) Air temperature is not effected by the aircraft range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The following cases happen if the final fuel weight increases in an aircraft:\n\nThe fuel ratio decreases as fuel ratio is the ratio of the initial fuel weight to final fuel weight\nThe range of the aircraft flying will be reduced.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "What is the relation between altitude and the aircraft range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altitude increases with increase in the aircraft range",
            "b) Altitude decreases with increase in the aircraft range",
            "c) Altitude increases with decrease in the aircraft range",
            "d) Altitude is not effected by the aircraft range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The air temperature increases with increase in the aircraft range. This is because the true airspeed (TAS) increases and the aircraft flies further in the given time during which it burns same quantity of the fuel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors are inversely proportional to the range of the aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altitude",
            "b) Ambient relative pressure",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Mach number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Altitude increases with increase in the aircraft range. As the altitude increases the ambient relative pressure decreases and it is further decreased due to the decreasing effect of the temperature with altitude.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct performance equation for power-producing engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ηV=PD",
            "b) ηD=PV",
            "c) ηP=VD",
            "d) V=ηPD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct equation for performance equation is ηP=VD where ŋ is propeller efficiency, P is drag power, D is drag and V is velocity. In a power-producing engine the shaft power is produced as well as propulsive thrust produced by the propeller which is converted into power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "What is the unit of specific fuel consumption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) kg/kW-sec",
            "b) kg/W-hr",
            "c) kg/hr",
            "d) kg/kW-hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unit of specific fuel consumption is given by kg/kW-hr. The formula for specific fuel consumption is C=\\(\\frac{Q_f}{P}\\) where Qf is fuel flow rate, P is power and C is specific fuel consumption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for specific fuel consumption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qf=\\(\\frac{P}{C}\\) ",
            "b) Qf=\\(\\frac{C}{P}\\) ",
            "c) C=\\(\\frac{P}{Q_f}\\) ",
            "d) C=\\(\\frac{Q_f}{P}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unit of specific fuel consumption is given by kg/kW-hr. The formula for specific fuel consumption is C=\\(\\frac{Q_f}{P}\\) where Qf is fuel flow rate, P is power and C is specific fuel consumption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "What is the value of specific fuel consumption where the fuel heating is 42,800kJ/kg and power produced is 5760 kW-hr?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.135 kg/kW-hr",
            "b) 7.43 kg/W-hr",
            "c) 1.546 kg/kW-hr",
            "d) 7.43 kg/kW-hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The answer is 7.43 kg/kW-hr. Given Qf=42,800 kJ/kg and P=5760 kW-hr. From the formula C=\\(\\frac{Q_f}{P}\\) we will find C. On substituting we get C=\\(\\frac{42800}{5760}\\).\nOn solving above equation we get the value of C=7.43 kg/kW-hr.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "What is the relation between specific air range and specific enurance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SAR=V*SE",
            "b) SAR=\\(\\frac{V}{SE}\\) ",
            "c) SE=V*SAR",
            "d) SE=\\(\\frac{V}{SAR}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific air range is maximum when the aircraft is flying at minimum drag speed and specific endurance is maximum when the aircraft is flying at minimum power speed. This is the same relation with thrust producing engines.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for specific air range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SAR=\\(\\frac{\\eta}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) ",
            "b) SAR=\\(\\frac{1}{PC}\\) ",
            "c) SAR=\\(\\frac{\\eta W}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\) ",
            "d) SAR=\\(\\frac{1}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific air range is maximum when the aircraft is flying at minimum drag speed and specific endurance is maximum when the aircraft is flying at minimum power speed. This is the same relation with thrust producing engines.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for specific endurance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SE=\\(\\frac{V}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) ",
            "b) SE=\\(\\frac{V}{PC}\\) ",
            "c) SE=\\(\\frac{\\eta}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) ",
            "d) SE=\\(\\frac{\\eta}{CV}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for specific air range is given by: SAR=\\(\\frac{V}{CP}\\) where v is velocity, C is specific fuel consumption and P is power. The formula for specific endurance is given by: SE=\\(\\frac{1}{CP}\\) where C is specific fuel consumption and P is power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "What is the value of specific air range where the lift to drag ratio is 10, weight is 50000N, efficiency is 85% and specific fuel consumption is 7.43 kg/kW-hr?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3000km",
            "b) 4000 km",
            "c) 1000km",
            "d) 5000km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct formula for specific air range is given by SAR=\\(\\frac{\\eta}{C}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) where η is propeller efficiency, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, W is weight. SAR can also be written as SAR=\\(\\frac{V}{CP}\\) where v is velocity, C is specific fuel consumption and P is power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "What is the value of specific endurance where the lift to drag ratio is 10, weight is 50000N, efficiency is 85% , velocity is 250m/s and specific fuel consumption is 7.43 kg/kW-hr?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30hr",
            "b) 57.6hr",
            "c) 10hr",
            "d) 50hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct formula for specific endurance is given by SE=\\(\\frac{\\eta}{CV}\\frac{L}{D}\\frac{1}{W}\\) where η is propeller efficiency, C is specific fuel consumption, L is lift, D is drag, V is velocity, W is weight. SE can also be written as SE=\\(\\frac{1}{CP}\\) where C is specific fuel consumption and P is power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "What is a turboprop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a combination of turbojet and ramjet",
            "b) It is a combination of turbojet and turbofan",
            "c) It is a combination of turbojet and scramjet",
            "d) It is a combination of turbojet and propeller engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Turbo-prop is a combination of turbojet and propeller engine. The power-plants used in turboprop are mixed power-plants i.e. it is a combination of both thrust producing engine and power producing engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "The residual energy is converted into __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) power",
            "b) thrust",
            "c) lift",
            "d) drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The residual energy in the exhaust is converted into thrust by the exhaust nozzle. The shaft power is converted into thrust through the propeller. This way the cruise performance characteristics of an aircraft wiith mixed power-plants lies between that of aircraft with pure thrust or pure power-producing plants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "What is the range of thrust producing engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RT=\\(\\big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C_T}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^4}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "b) RT=\\(\\big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C_T}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "c) RT=\\(\\big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C_T}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "d) RT=\\(\\big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C_T}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{u^3}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct equation for range of thrust producing engine is given by the equation RT=\\(\\big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C_T}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, Emax is endurance  and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "What is the range of the power producing engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RP=\\(\\big[\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "b) RP=\\(\\big[\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "c) RP=\\(\\big[\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "d) RP=\\(\\big[\\frac{V_{mdi}}{C_P}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^3}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct equation for range of thrust producing engine is given by the equation RP=\\(\\big[\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}E_{max}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω where V is true airspeed, C is specific fuel consumption, Emax is endurance, η is propeller efficiency and ω is fuel ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "What is the range formula for mixed power-plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R=Emax\\(\\big[Π\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}+(1+Π)\\frac{uV_{md}}{C_T}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4-1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "b) R=Emax\\(\\big[Π\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}+(1-Π)\\frac{uV_{md}}{C_T}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4-1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "c) R=Emax\\(\\big[Π\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}+(1-Π)\\frac{uV_{md}}{C_T}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω",
            "d) R=Emax\\(\\big[Π\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}+(1+Π)\\frac{uV_{md}}{C_T}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The range formula for mixed power-plant is given by the equation R=Emax\\(\\big[Π\\frac{\\eta}{C_P}+(1-Π)\\frac{uV_{md}}{C_T}\\big]\\big\\{\\frac{2u^2}{u^4+1}\\big\\}\\)lnω where Π is the proportion of thrust derived from the shaft power in the overall thrust of the power-plant, CT, CP are the specific fuel consumption of thrust producing and power producing engines,  Emax is endurance and V is true airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ESHP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equivalent shaft horsepower",
            "b) Equal shaft horsepower",
            "c) Engine shaft horsepower",
            "d) Endurance shaft horsepower"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ESPH stands for Equivalent shaft horsepower. It is the combination of thrust output with the shaft power output to give the total output in power form as if the engine was a pure power producing engine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct thrust balancing equation for thrust producing engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FN+D=Wsinγ2+mV̇",
            "b) FN-D=Wsinγ2+mV̇",
            "c) FN-D=Wsinγ2-mV̇",
            "d) FN+D=Wsinγ2-mV̇"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct thrust balancing equation for thrust producing engines is given by the equation FN-D=Wsinγ2+mV̇ where FN is the normal force acting on the aircraft, γ is the angle at which the force is acting on the aircraft, D is drag produced, W is weight of the aircraft, m is mass and V̇ is velocity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct lift balancing equation for thrust producing engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L=Wcosγ2",
            "b) L=Wsinγ2",
            "c) L=\\(\\frac{cos\\gamma _2}{W}\\) ",
            "d) L=\\(\\frac{sin\\gamma_2}{W}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct lift balancing equation for thrust producing engines is given by the equation L=Wcosγ2 where L is lift, W is weight and γ is the angle at which the force is acting on the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "What should be the value of thrust- to-weight ratio for a normal take-off so that the acceleration associated with the rate of climb is neglected?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 0.2",
            "c) 0.3",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 0.3 must be the value of thrust- to-weight ratio for a normal take-off so that the acceleration associated with the rate of climb is neglected. This way the climb can be assumed with constant airspeed and mach number.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "What is the relation between thrust power and true airspeed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust power increases with increase in true airspeed",
            "b) Thrust power decreases with increase in true airspeed",
            "c) Thrust power increases with decrease in true airspeed",
            "d) Thrust power is independent of true airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The best gradient of climb is attained at the time of minimum drag speed of the aircraft. The best gradient of climb is attained generally at the airspeed ‘u’ of 1. The gradient of climb is given by Emaxsinγ2=τ-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2].\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "In which of the following the maximum rate of climb occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It occurs when difference in thrust power and drag power is minimum",
            "b) It occurs when difference in thrust power and drag power is maximum",
            "c) It occurs when difference in thrust power is minimum",
            "d) It occurs when difference in drag power is minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The best rate of climb occurs when the excess thrust power (FNV) is maximum than the drag power (DV). As the ideal power increases linearly with true airspeed the best gradient of climb is predicted to be at an airspeed greater than minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct climb gradient equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) τ-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emaxsinγ2",
            "b) τ+\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emaxsinγ2",
            "c) τ+\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emax",
            "d) τ-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The best rate of climb occurs when the excess thrust power (FNV) is maximum than the drag power (DV). As the ideal power increases linearly with true airspeed the best gradient of climb is predicted to be at an airspeed greater than minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "At what airspeed does maximum gradient of climb occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thrust power increases with increase in true airspeed.The best rate of climb occurs when the excess thrust power (FNV) is maximum than the drag power (DV). As the ideal power increases linearly with true airspeed the best gradient of climb is predicted to be at an airspeed greater than minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct rate of climb equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) τu-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u3+u-1]=Emaxv",
            "b) τ-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emaxsinγ2",
            "c) τ+\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emaxsinγ2",
            "d) τu-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u3+u-1]=Emaxv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum rate of climb occurs when the difference in thrust power and drag power is maximum. The rate of climb is a function of excess thrust power.The best rate of climb occurs when the excess thrust power (FNV) is maximum than the drag power (DV).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "What is the correct formula for dimensionless rate of climb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ν=\\(\\frac{dH/dt}{V_{md}}\\) ",
            "b) v=\\(\\frac{V_{md}}{dH/dt}\\) ",
            "c) v=\\(\\frac{-V_{md}}{dH/dt}\\) ",
            "d) v=\\(\\frac{-dH/dt}{V_{md}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct climb gradient equation is given by the equation τ-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emaxsinγ2 where τ is dimensionless thrust, u is airspeed, Emax is endurance and γ is the angle at which the force is acting on the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "What is the benefit of flying at minimum power speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases gliding flight time",
            "b) Decreases gliding flight time",
            "c) Does not change the gliding flight time",
            "d) Decreases the aircraft performance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum gradient of climb occurs at airspeed (u) =1. There occurs negative values for sinγ2  of τ and u when the flight is descending. The climb gradient equation is given by the equation τ-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u2+u-2]=Emaxsinγ2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "What is the value that maintains minimum power speed of the aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) u/\\(\\sqrt[4]{3}\\) ",
            "b) u/\\(\\sqrt[3]{3}\\) ",
            "c) u2/\\(\\sqrt[4]{3}\\) ",
            "d) u2/\\(\\sqrt[3]{3}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct rate of climb equation is given by τu-\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)[u3+u-1]=Emaxv where τ is dimensionless thrust, u is airspeed, Emax is endurance and γ is the angle at which the force is acting on the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The propulsive force developed by the engine-propeller combination is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{\\eta V}{P}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{\\eta P}{V}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{P}{V}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{VP}{\\eta}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The propulsive force developed by the engine-propeller combination is given by \\(\\frac{\\eta P}{V}\\) where η is propeller efficiency, P is power and V is velocity. The equation of power-producing engine is written as \\(\\frac{\\eta P}{V}\\)-D=Wsinγ2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "The gradient of climb is given by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\Big[\\frac{\\eta P}{V}-W\\Big]\\frac{1}{D}\\)=sinγ2",
            "b) \\(\\Big[\\frac{\\eta P}{V}+D\\Big]\\frac{1}{W}\\)=sinγ2",
            "c) \\(\\Big[\\frac{\\eta P}{V}-D\\Big]\\frac{1}{W}\\)=sinγ2",
            "d) \\(\\Big[\\frac{\\eta P}{V}+W\\Big]\\frac{1}{D}\\)=sinγ2"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The gradient of climb is given by \\(\\Big[\\frac{\\eta P}{V}-D\\Big]\\frac{1}{W}\\)=sinγ2 where η is propeller efficiency, P is power, V is velocity, D is drag and γ is the angle at which the force is acting on the aircraft. The value of gradient of climb is more when the propulsive force is maximum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "The rate of climb is given by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) [ηP+DV]\\(\\frac{1}{W}\\)=\\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) ",
            "b) [ηP-DV]\\(\\frac{1}{W}\\)=\\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) ",
            "c) [ηP+DV]W=\\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) ",
            "d) [ηP-DV]W=\\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of climb is given by [ηP-DV]\\(\\frac{1}{W}\\)=\\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) where η is propeller efficiency, P is power, V is velocity, D is drag and W is weight and dH/dt is vertical velocity. The rate of climb is maximum when power speed is minimum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "What is the relation between climb rate and power speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climb rate increases at minimum power drag",
            "b) Climb rate decreases at minimum power drag",
            "c) Climb rate is independent of minimum power drag",
            "d) Climb rate increases at maximum power drag"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Climb rate is maximum at minimum power drag. The rate of climb is given by [ηP-DV]\\(\\frac{1}{W}\\)=\\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) where η is propeller efficiency, P is power, V is velocity, D is drag and W is weight and dH/dt is vertical velocity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "What is the value of λ in gliding flight flying at minimum drag speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The relative airspeed for maximum gradient of climb is a function of engine power. The best climb gradient is given by u4+λu-1=0 where u is airspeed and λ is dimensionless power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "What is the relation betweenpower and airspeed for climb gradient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power increases with increase in airspeed",
            "b) Power decreases with increase in airspeed",
            "c) Power increases with decrease in airspeed",
            "d) Power is unaffected by the airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: In gliding flight the value of dimensionless power (λ) is zero (0) and the shallow glide angle is given by flying at the minimum drag speed. As the power increase the airspeed for maximum climb gradient decreases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "What is the value that maintains maximum rate and minimum power speed of the aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/\\(\\sqrt[4]{3}\\) ",
            "b) 1/\\(\\sqrt[3]{3}\\) ",
            "c) u2/\\(\\sqrt[4]{3}\\) ",
            "d) u2/\\(\\sqrt[3]{3}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The relation between power and airspeed for climb gradient is that the power increases with decrease in airspeed for maximum climb gradient. The best climb gradient is attained by flying at airspeeds less than the minimum power speeds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "At what rate does the minimum sink rate occur in a gliding flight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It occurs at minimum power speed",
            "b) It occurs at maximum power speed",
            "c) It occurs at minimum airspeed",
            "d) It occurs at maximum airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The relation between power and airspeed for climb gradient is that the power increases with decrease in airspeed for maximum climb gradient. The best climb gradient is attained by flying at airspeeds less than the minimum power speeds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct performance equation for mixed power-plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emaxsinγ2=\\(\\Big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}+\\tau \\Big]-\\frac{1}{2}[u^2+u^{-2}]\\) ",
            "b) Emaxsinγ2=\\(\\Big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}-\\tau \\Big]-\\frac{1}{2}[u^2-u^{-2}]\\) ",
            "c) Emaxsinγ2=\\(\\Big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}+\\tau \\Big]-\\frac{1}{2}[u^2-u^{-2}]\\) ",
            "d) Emaxsinγ2=\\(\\Big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}-\\tau \\Big]-\\frac{1}{2}[u^2+u^{-2}]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct performance equation for mixed power-plants is given by the formula Emaxsinγ2=\\(\\Big[\\frac{\\lambda}{u}+\\tau \\Big]-\\frac{1}{2}[u^2+u^{-2}]\\) where u is airspeed, γ is the angle at which the force is acting on the aircraft and τ is dimensionless thrust and Emax is endurance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The best gradient of climb is attained at _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) airspeed below maximum drag speed",
            "b) airspeed below maximum power speed",
            "c) airspeed below minimum power speed",
            "d) airspeed below minimum drag speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The best gradient of climb is attained at airspeed below minimum drag speed. The best rate of climb is attained at airspeed above minimum drag speed. The actual airspeeds will be a function of excess propulsive thrust.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "The best rate of climb is attained at _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) airspeed above maximum drag speed",
            "b) airspeed above maximum power speed",
            "c) airspeed above minimum power speed",
            "d) airspeed above minimum drag speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The best gradient of climb is attained at airspeed below minimum drag speed. The best rate of climb is attained at airspeed above minimum drag speed. The actual airspeeds will be a function of excess propulsive thrust.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "At which speed the maximum rate of climb occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) u=0.76",
            "b) u=0.98",
            "c) u=1",
            "d) u=2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum rate of climb occurs at the airspeed u=0.76 m/sec. The best gradient of climb is attained at airspeed below minimum drag speed. The best rate of climb is attained at airspeed above minimum drag speed. The actual airspeeds will be a function of excess propulsive thrust.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "The rate of climb of an aircraft is measured by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) variometer",
            "b) altimeter",
            "c) pitot-static prob",
            "d) gyroscope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rate of climb of an aircraft is measured by variometer. The best gradient of climb is attained at airspeed below minimum drag speed. The best rate of climb is attained at airspeed above minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "The advanced ratio is given by _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) J=\\(\\frac{D}{nV}\\) ",
            "b) J=\\(\\frac{nV}{D}\\) ",
            "c) J=\\(\\frac{V}{nD}\\) ",
            "d) J=\\(\\frac{n}{VD}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The advanced ratio is given by J=\\(\\frac{V}{nD}\\) where J is advance ratio, V is velocity and D is propeller diameter and n is rotational speed. Propeller efficiency is depended on advanced ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "What is the use of partial climbs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used for calculating climb rate",
            "b) It is used for calculating gradient of climb",
            "c) It is used for calculating speed",
            "d) It is used for calculating velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The use of partial climbs is to calculate rate of climb. The other method for calculating climb rate is level accelerated method. Level accelerated is best suitable for thrust producing engines. Partial climb is best suitable for power-producing engines.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "What is departure path?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A path of no obstructions",
            "b) Runway path",
            "c) Apron area",
            "d) Passenger terminal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The departure path is defined as the path which is free from obstacles and the landing or take-off is guaranteed a safe and clear flight path. It is complex and depends on the size of the size of airfield and aircraft operations that are performed in that airport.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "The departure path in an airport is depended on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) size of the runway",
            "b) size of the airfield",
            "c) maneuvers done by the aircraft",
            "d) fuel content in the aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The departure path is defined as the path which is free from obstacles and the landing or take-off is guaranteed a safe and clear flight path. It is complex and depends on the size of the size of airfield and aircraft operations that are performed in that airport.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "What is the distance of the safeguard path?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25000m",
            "b) 30000m",
            "c) 35000m",
            "d) 15000m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The safeguard distance of the runway is 1500m. The safeguard path has a gradient of 2%. The safeguard distance extends from the take-off distance available on the runway to a distance of 15000m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "What is the gradient of climb for one engine inoperative?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2%",
            "b) 3%",
            "c) 4%",
            "d) 5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gradient of climb for one engine inoperative is 2%. This is same in all conditions and also during the emergency conditions of one engine inoperative. In this situation the engine works at maximum airspeed required for best gradient of climb.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives the best gradient of climb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low airspeed which is closer to critical operating airspeed",
            "b) High airspeed which is closer to critical operating airspeed",
            "c) At any airspeed",
            "d) At high bypass ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The airspeed chosen for after take-off climb should be same as for that of maximum gradient.The safeguard path has a gradient of 2%. The safeguard distance extends from the take-off distance available on the runway to a distance of 15000m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which part of the flight is more crucial?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Take-off path",
            "b) Landing path",
            "c) After take-off path",
            "d) Before landing path"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The best gradient of climb is achieved when the airspeed is low and closer to that of the critical operating speed. The safeguard path has a gradient of 2%. The safeguard distance extends from the take-off distance available on the runway to a distance of 15000m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct according to power producing engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airspeed for climb is high than for optimum climb gradient",
            "b) Airspeed for climb is less than for optimum climb gradient",
            "c) Airspeed for climb is equal to optimum climb gradient",
            "d) Airspeed for climb is equal to maximum climb gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most crucial and critical path in the flight path is the after take-off path. This is obtained by extending landing gears and flaps set to optimize take-off speed and runway distance requirement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "What are the restrictions on the airspeed scheduled for climb gradient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Safe margining over the stall airspeed",
            "b) Fuel management",
            "c) Speed control",
            "d) Altitude check"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The airspeed for climb is high than for optimum climb gradient in the case of power producing engines. The airspeed chosen for after take-off climb should be same as for that of maximum gradient. The safeguard path has a gradient of 2%. The safeguard distance extends from the take-off distance available on the runway to a distance of 15000m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct safe height of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20000m",
            "b) 15000m",
            "c) 30000m",
            "d) 40000m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The safe height of an aircraft for take-off above the airfield is 15000m. The use of safe height is to avoid ground based obstacles and make a clear flight path to avoid aircraft collision and loss of life and property.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "The best economic flight is achieved by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum drag",
            "b) minimum speed",
            "c) minimum drag",
            "d) maximum fuel consumption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The operating height is achieved by maximum rate climb. The safe height of an aircraft for take-off above the airfield is 15000m. The use of safe height is to avoid ground based obstacles and make a clear flight path to avoid aircraft collision and loss of life and property.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What is climb rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The rate at which the flight take-off the ground",
            "b) Speed at which the flight takes-off",
            "c) Distance required for flight to take-off",
            "d) Fuel required for the take-off of flight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The best economic flight is achieved by minimum drag speed and take minimum time to climb. It is must that the flight path is obstruction free and need to continue flight without any stop before take-off.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "The thrust required during the take-off is a function of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) time",
            "b) fuel",
            "c) weight",
            "d) lift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The airspeed best for rate of climb to close to that of their minimum drag speed. The operating height is achieved by maximum rate climb. The safe height of an aircraft for take-off above the airfield is 15000m. The use of safe height is to avoid ground based obstacles and make a clear flight path to avoid aircraft collision and loss of life and property.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the formula for specific climb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SC=\\(\\frac{dH}{Q_f}\\) ",
            "b) SC=\\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) ",
            "c) SC=\\(\\frac{dH/dt}{Q_f}\\)c ",
            "d) SC=\\(\\frac{dH/dt}{Q_f}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula for specific climb is given by SC=\\(\\frac{dH/dt}{Q_f}\\) where SC is specific thrust, \\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) is rate change of height with respect to time and Qf is fuel flow. The specific climb is calculated in the units of ft/kg.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What is the value of specific climb when the value of \\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\)=1 and the fuel flow is 833.33 kg?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0013ft/kg",
            "b) 0.0012ft/kg",
            "c) 0.0019ft/kg",
            "d) 0.002ft/kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:The formula for specific climb is given by SC=\\(\\frac{dH/dt}{Q_f}\\) where SC is specific thrust, \\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\) is rate change of height with respect to time and Qf is fuel flow. The specific climb is calculated in the units of ft/kg.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Which of the following characteristics are determined during flight trials of calculated fuel flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel rate",
            "b) Optimum climb speed",
            "c) Airspeed",
            "d) Altitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The answer is 0.0012ft/kg. The formula for specific climb is given by SC=\\(\\frac{dH/dt}{Q_f}\\). Given, \\(\\frac{dH}{dt}\\)=1 and Qf=833.33 kg. Substituting the values we get SC=\\(\\frac{1}{833.33}\\).\nWe get SC=0.0012ft/kg.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "The thrust reduction during climb leads to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase in rate of climb",
            "b) reduction in time of flight",
            "c) increase in gradient of climb",
            "d) decrease in climb gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the calculated fuel flow flight trials the optimum climb speed is calculated and then the specific climb function is known which helps in the determination of airspeed for a minimum fuel climb.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "What are the factors that affect the economic benefits of fuel climb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirect operating costs",
            "b) Direct operating costs",
            "c) Annual pay to the airport",
            "d) Tax pay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum fuel climb occurs at the airspeed for best rate of climb. During the calculated fuel flow flight trials the optimum climb speed is calculated and then the specific climb function is known which helps in the determination of airspeed for a minimum fuel climb.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "In what proportion should the propulsive thrust be so that the aircraft will decelerate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust is less than airframe drag",
            "b) Thrust is more than airframe drag",
            "c) Greater airspeed",
            "d) Less airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aircraft will descend if the propulsive thrust is less than the airframe drag. The descend flight path can be varied from a shallow descent to a very steep descent either by reducing the engine thrust or by increasing airframe drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "What are the factors for that increase the drag in an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Varying airspeed",
            "b) Constant airspeed",
            "c) Varying thrust",
            "d) Varying fuel ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aircraft will descend if the propulsive thrust is less than the airframe drag. The descend flight path can be varied from a shallow descent to a very steep descent either by reducing the engine thrust or by increasing airframe drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "At which cases does descent of flow occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By flying the aircraft at airspeed less than minimum drag speed",
            "b) By flying the aircraft at airspeed more than minimum drag speed",
            "c) By flying the aircraft at airspeed less than maximum drag speed",
            "d) By flying the aircraft at airspeed more than maximum drag speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The drag that is produced in the aircraft is increased by aerodynamic means or by varying the airspeed. The aircraft has a very wide range of descent path for the aircrafts. The aircraft will descend if the propulsive thrust is less than the airframe drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "The flight path is unstable during __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the aircraft flying at airspeed less than minimum drag speed",
            "b) the aircraft flying at airspeed more than minimum drag speed",
            "c) the aircraft flying at airspeed less than maximum drag speed",
            "d) the aircraft flying at airspeed more than maximum drag speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of gliders, the descent is calculated by lift-drag ratio. In this case the minimum rate of descent occurs at the minimum power speed and minimum gradient occurs at the minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "The flight path can be controlled by the use of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) elevator",
            "b) rudder",
            "c) flaps",
            "d) slats"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The descent of an aircraft can happen at flying the aircraft at airspeed less than minimum drag speed. In this case the minimum rate of descent occurs at the minimum power speed and minimum gradient occurs at the minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "By which of the methods the flight can be descended?",
        "Options": [
            "a) nose down pitch",
            "b) nose uppitch",
            "c) nose down and elevator",
            "d) elevator and nose up"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flight path is unstable during the aircraft flying at airspeed less than minimum drag speed. In this case the minimum rate of descent occurs at the minimum power speed and minimum gradient occurs at the minimum drag speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "What measures are taken to maintain precise control of flight path gradient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elevator settings alone",
            "b) Thrust settings alone",
            "c) Elevator and thrust settings",
            "d) Flap settings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the back side of the drag curve the rate of change of drag is negative. During this case the flight path gradient cannot be alone handled by the elevator control. If the aircraft is flying with airspeed greater than minimum drag speed then the flight path gradient of descent can be increased by increasing airspeed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "The rate of the change in the cabin pressure should not exceed ______ at sea level.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 ft/min",
            "b) 3000 ft/min",
            "c) 3 ft/min",
            "d) 300 ft/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The precise control of the flight path gradient is achieved by the changes in the thrust of the flight along with the elevator control inputs given to the system during the gradient of descent of the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "What is the required time of descend for flight gradient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 min",
            "b) 15min",
            "c) 24min",
            "d) 70min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Accurate manual control of the flight path will be difficult to handle without the auto-throttle. The precise control of the flight path gradient is achieved by the changes in the thrust of the flight along with the elevator control inputs given to the system during the gradient of descent of the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "The gradient of descent is ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15%",
            "b) 11%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 18%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rate of the change in the cabin pressure should not exceed 300 ft/min at sea level. This states that the cabin is pressurized to 8000ft pressure height, the descent to the sea level should not exceed 24 minutes before the take-off.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "The aircraft is taken to the level ground operating for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) considering vertical component of the wind",
            "b) considering horizontal component of the wind",
            "c) considering both horizontal and vertical component of the wind",
            "d) neglecting the effect of wind"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wind is the relative velocity between the air mass and the ground. Usually wind is assumed to have only a horizontal component but there exists vertical component which may affect the aircraft at considerable height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "The relative velocity of the wind produces boundary layer close to the ground which ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) decreases the wind speed with decrease in height",
            "b) increases the wind speed with decrease in height",
            "c) makes the wind speed unaffected",
            "d) constantly increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The aircraft is taken to the level ground operating for considering horizontal component of the wind. Wind is the relative velocity between the air mass and the ground. Usually wind is assumed to have only a horizontal component but there exists vertical component which may affect the aircraft at considerable height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "The flight path is calculated relative to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) air mass",
            "b) still air condition",
            "c) air mass and still air condition",
            "d) airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relative velocity of the wind produces boundary layer close to the ground which decreases the wind speed with decrease in height. This will further produce effects on the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "What is meant by perceived performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Visualization of the aircraft with respect to wind",
            "b) Visualization of the aircraft with respect to aircraft relative to ground",
            "c) Visualization of the aircraft with respect to wind with respect to ground",
            "d) Visualization of the aircraft with respect to any one frame such as aircraft or ground"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flight path is calculated relative to air mass. This resulted in the development of the theory by experimenting in the still air condition. In actual performance of the aircraft the relative velocity is not effected by the reference axis as they are velocity axes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "The horizontal component of the true airspeed is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increased by tailwind",
            "b) decreased by tailwind",
            "c) increased by headwind",
            "d) unaffected by the airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is assumed zero velocity datum at the center of gravity (CG) of the aircraft. Centre of gravity (CG) of an aircraft is the point at which the whole weight of the aircraft is being balanced. This CG does not change with respect to speed of the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "What is wind shear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The extreme case of airspeed effect on the aircraft",
            "b) The extreme case of wind effect on the aircraft",
            "c) The extreme case of temperature effect on the wind",
            "d) The extreme case of altitude effect on the wind"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The performance relative to ground is effected by the wind. The relative velocity of the wind produces boundary layer close to the ground which decreases the wind speed with decrease in height. This will further produce effects on the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "If ETS is 400kts, what is the acceleration associated with it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40kts/min",
            "b) 4000kts/min",
            "c) 4kts/min",
            "d) 400kts/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If ETS is 400kts, then the associated acceleration with it is 400kts/min. This is during the climb phase of the aircraft. Thus it concludes that the climb is the combination of the potential and kinetic energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Specific total energy is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the potential energy per unit mass",
            "b) the kinetic energy per unit mass",
            "c) the potential and kinetic energy per unit mass",
            "d) the potential and kinetic energy per unit time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Specific total energy is the potential and kinetic energy per unit mass. This is few times referred as the energy height as it represents the height of the aircraft would attain if all the kinetic energy is converted to potential energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "STE stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard total energy",
            "b) Specific terminal energy",
            "c) Standard terminal energy",
            "d) Specific total energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Specific total energy is the potential and kinetic energy per unit mass. This is few times referred as the energy height as it represents the height of the aircraft would attain if all the kinetic energy is converted to potential energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for STE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Es=\\(\\Big\\{H-\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "b) Es=\\(\\Big\\{H+\\frac{V^2}{g}\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "c) Es=\\(\\Big\\{H+\\frac{V^2}{2}\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "d) Es=\\(\\Big\\{H+\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct formula for specific total energy is given by the formula Es=\\(\\Big\\{H+\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\) where ‘Es’ is specific total energy, ‘H’ is height, ‘V’ is velocity and ‘g’ is acceleration due to gravity. Specific total energy is the potential and kinetic energy per unit mass. This is few times referred as the energy height as it represents the height of the aircraft would attain if all the kinetic energy is converted to potential energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "SEP stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific Efficient Power",
            "b) Specific Excess Power",
            "c) Standard Efficient Power",
            "d) Standard Excess Power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SEP stands for specific excess power. It is equal to the rate of change of specific total energy (STE) and is used to increase the total energy of the aircraft which is in a combination with climb and acceleration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "The formula for SEP is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) [FN-D]\\(\\frac{V}{W}=\\frac{d}{dt}\\Big\\{H+\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "b) [FN+D]\\(\\frac{V}{W}=\\frac{d}{dt}\\Big\\{H+\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "c) [FN-D]\\(\\frac{V}{W}=\\frac{d}{dt}\\Big\\{H-\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "d) [FN+D]\\(\\frac{V}{W}=\\frac{d}{dt}\\Big\\{H-\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for SEP is given by [FN-D]\\(\\frac{V}{W}=\\frac{d}{dt}\\Big\\{H+\\frac{V^2}{2g}\\Big\\}\\) where FN is force, D is drag, H is height, V is velocity, g is acceleration due to gravitation. SEP stands for specific excess power. It is equal to the rate of change of specific total energy (STE) and is used to increase the total energy of the aircraft which is in a combination with climb and acceleration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "What are the methods followed to gain advantage in air to air combat mission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accelerate to the operational height in a short time",
            "b) Decelerate to the operational height in a short time",
            "c) Accelerate to the operational height in a long time",
            "d) Decelerate to the operational height in a long time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gain in advantage of air to air combat mission is gained by accelerating to the operational height in a short time and obtaining an optimum mach number in that short span of time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "What is the operational technique in combat mission aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimizing the time required to increase the total energy of the aircraft to its combat height",
            "b) Maximizing the time required to decrease the total energy of the aircraft to its combat height",
            "c) Minimizing the time required to decrease the total energy of the aircraft to its combat height",
            "d) Minimizing the time required to increase the total energy of the aircraft to its combat height"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The operational technique in combat mission aircraft is to minimize the time required to increase the total energy of the aircraft to its combat height. The gain in advantage of air to air combat mission is gained by accelerating to the operational height in a short time and obtaining an optimum mach number in that short span of time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "What are the terminal phases of the aircraft landing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Take-off",
            "b) Landing",
            "c) Take-off and landing",
            "d) En-route"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The terminal phases of the aircraft are the take-off phase at the departure and landing at the destination. In the take-off phase the aircraft is transformed to safe airborne state from the stationary ground state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "What is engine failure accountability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) management of landing during the engine failure",
            "b) management of take-off during the engine failure",
            "c) fuel management during the engine failure",
            "d) thrust management during the engine failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The terminal phases consist of two parts. They are ground run distance and airborne distance. The terminal phases of the aircraft are the take-off phase at the departure and landing at the destination. In the take-off phase the aircraft is transformed to safe airborne state from the stationary ground state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "What is aspect ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the ratio of square of wing span to wing area",
            "b) It is the ratio of wing span to wing area",
            "c) It is the ratio of square of wing area to wing span",
            "d) It is the ratio of wing area to wing span"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The engine failure accountability is the management of landing during the engine failure. The length of runway depends on the purpose of aircraft and also the length and size of the aircraft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "What is the formula of aspect ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AS=\\(\\frac{b}{S}\\) ",
            "b) AS=\\(\\frac{s}{b}\\) ",
            "c) AS=\\(\\frac{S^2}{b}\\) ",
            "d) AS=\\(\\frac{b^2}{S}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aspect ratio is the ratio of the square of wing span to wing area. It is given by the formula, AS=\\(\\frac{b^2}{S}\\) where AS is aspect ratio, b is wing span and S is wing area.  In general the aspect ratio is maintained high in the aircraft for structural rigidity and reducing drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "What is the aspect ratio when the wing is 10 feet long and 2 feet wide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aspect ratio is the ratio of the square of wing span to wing area. It is given by the formula, AS=\\(\\frac{b^2}{S}\\) where AS is aspect ratio, b is wing span and S is wing area.  In general the aspect ratio is maintained high in the aircraft for structural rigidity and reducing drag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Ski-jump take-off path is used by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) military aircrafts",
            "b) commercial aircrafts",
            "c) passenger aircrafts",
            "d) cargo aircrafts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aspect ratio is given by the ratio of span and chord. Given span = 10 feet and chord is 2 feet. Substituting in the formula we get AS=\\(\\frac{span}{chord}\\). AS=\\(\\frac{10}{2}\\).\nAS=5.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the correct type of take-off and landings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) reduced take-off and landing, short take-off and landing, vertical take-off and landing",
            "b) short take-off and landing, vertical take-off and landing",
            "c) convectional take-off and landing, reduced take-off and landing",
            "d) convectional take-off and landing, reduced take-off and landing, short take-off and landing, vertical take-off and landing, short take-off and vertical landing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ski-jump take-off path is the path which has an elevation at the end of the runway i.e. the road is lifted up with respect to ground at an angle. This ski-jump assisted angle is approximately equal to 12°.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not heavy lift devices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) full span flaps",
            "b) drooped ailerons",
            "c) passive boundary layer control systems",
            "d) elevator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are five types of take-off and landings. They are:\n\nCTOL- convectional take-off and landing\nRTOL- reduced take-off and landing\nSTOL- short take-off and landing\nVTOL- vertical take-off and landing \nSTOVL- short take-off and vertical landing.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "How is the power-induced lift generated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) installing the propeller in front of the wing",
            "b) installing the propeller in front of the wing and deflecting the slip stream with large flaps",
            "c) deflecting the slip stream with large flaps",
            "d) deflecting the slip stream with large rudder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aircraft uses short take-off landing to reduce the take-off fuel demand. This results in take-off of the aircraft with the weight of the aircraft above maximum vertical take-off and landing (VTOL) weight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "What is meant by minimum control speed ground?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The airspeed below which the rudder the will not be capable of producing a yawing moment",
            "b) The airspeed below which the rudder the will not be capable of producing a pitching moment",
            "c) The airspeed below which the rudder the will not be capable of producing a rolling moment",
            "d) The airspeed below which the rudder the will not be capable of producing a dutch moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum control speed ground is the airspeed below which the rudder the will not be capable of producing a yawing moment. If there is an engine failure at this moment then it is must to stop the take-off run.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "What is lift-off speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The speed at which the aircraft generates enough power to become airborne",
            "b) The speed at which the aircraft generates enough speed to become airborne",
            "c) The speed at which the aircraft generates enough thrust to become airborne",
            "d) The speed at which the aircraft generates enough lift to become airborne"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The lift-off speed is the speed at which the aircraft generates enough lift to become airborne. Just before reaching this speed the aircraft rotates into a nose-up altitude which is equal to the lift-off angle of attack.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "What is the screen height during the take-off of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 ft",
            "b) 14 ft",
            "c) 30 ft",
            "d) 35 ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lift-off speed is the speed at which the aircraft generates enough lift to become airborne. Just before reaching this speed the aircraft rotates into a nose-up altitude which is equal to the lift-off angle of attack.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "What is meant by ground run distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The distance where the aircraft takes-off on the ground",
            "b) The vertical distance where the aircraft takes-off on the ground",
            "c) It is also known as the screen height",
            "d) It is the landing distance of the aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The take-off speed for the aircraft is known to be 35 feet from the ground level. The screen height is same for all types of aircraft such as commercial, combat etc. This screen height is maintained same to avoid aircraft collision.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "What is the use of minimum control speed airborne?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maintain directional control",
            "b) Maintain fuel ratio",
            "c) Maintain constant thrust",
            "d) Maintain constant power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rotation speed must allow the aircraft to rotate into lift-off attitude before the lift-off speed is being achieved by the aircraft. Just before reaching lift-off speed the aircraft rotates into a nose-up altitude which is equal to the lift-off angle of attack.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "What is meant by take-off safety speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airspeed at which only the safe climb gradient is attained",
            "b) Airspeed at which only the directional control is attained",
            "c) Airspeed at which only the directional control is kept constant",
            "d) Airspeed at which both the safe climb gradient and directional control is attained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ground run distance is the distance where the aircraft takes-off on the ground. There are two parts of take-off distance. One is ground distance and the other one is the distance from which the aircraft leaves the ground. This screen height must be about 35 feet to avoid aircraft collision.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "What is meant by decision speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The speed at the point where there is unequal distances on the take-off run",
            "b) The slope at the point where there is unequal distances on the take-off run",
            "c) The slope at the point where there is equal distances on the take-off run",
            "d) The speed at the point where there is equal distances on the take-off run"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two parts of take-off distance. One is ground distance and the other one is the distance from which the aircraft leaves the ground. This screen height must be about 35 feet to avoid aircraft collision.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "What is meant by airborne distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The distance between take-off point and the point at which the screen height is cleared",
            "b) The distance between lift-off point and the point at which the screen height is not cleared",
            "c) The distance between lift-off point and the point at which the screen height is cleared",
            "d) The distance between take-off point and the point at which the screen height is not cleared"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum control speed airborne is used to maintain the directional control during the climb of the aircraft. The minimum control speed airborne is always greater than the minimum control speed ground.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "What is meant by minimum unstick speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The maximum speed at which the aircraft becomes airborne",
            "b) The minimum speed at which the aircraft does not becomes airborne",
            "c) The maximum speed at which the aircraft does not becomes airborne",
            "d) The minimum speed at which the aircraft becomes airborne"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The take-off safety speed is the airspeed at which both the safe climb gradient and directional control is attained. This condition is attained at the time of engine failure in the airborne state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "What are the additional forces acting on the aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Runway friction",
            "b) Lift",
            "c) Thrust",
            "d) Power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The additional forces that act on the aircraft are:\n\nRunway friction\nWheel spin-up\nSide-wind loads.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the correct equations for take-off run?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FN+D-WsinγR-μrR=mV̇",
            "b) R-L=WcosγR",
            "c) R-L=WsinγR",
            "d) FN-D-WsinγR-μrR=mV̇"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The equations derived for the take-off run are as follows:\n\nFN-D-WsinγR-μrR=mV̇\nR+L=WcosγR\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for accelerating force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{F}{W}=\\Big\\{\\frac{F_N}{W}+\\mu_R-sin\\gamma_R\\Big\\}-\\frac{L}{W}\\Big(\\frac{C_D}{C_L}-\\mu_R\\Big)\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{F}{W}=\\Big\\{\\frac{F_N}{W}-\\mu_R+sin\\gamma_R\\Big\\}-\\frac{L}{W}\\Big(\\frac{C_D}{C_L}-\\mu_R\\Big)\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{F}{W}=\\Big\\{\\frac{F_N}{W}-\\mu_R-sin\\gamma_R\\Big\\}-\\frac{L}{W}\\Big(\\frac{C_D}{C_L}-\\mu_R\\Big)\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{F}{W}=\\Big\\{\\frac{F_N}{W}-\\mu_R-sin\\gamma_R\\Big\\}-\\frac{L}{W}\\Big(\\frac{C_D}{C_L}+\\mu_R\\Big)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula for accelerating force is given by: \\(\\frac{F}{W}=\\Big\\{\\frac{F_N}{W}-\\mu_R-sin\\gamma_R\\Big\\}-\\frac{L}{W}\\Big(\\frac{C_D}{C_L}-\\mu_R\\Big)\\) where F is force, W is weight, μR is runway coefficient of the rolling friction, γR is runway slope, L is lift, CD and CL are the coefficients of drag and lift.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "The formula for ground run is given by the formula __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SG=\\(\\frac{V_{LOF}^2}{2g(A+BV^2)_{V_{LOF}}}\\) ",
            "b) SG=\\(\\frac{V_{LOF}^2}{2g(A+BV^2)_{0.7V_{LOF}}}\\) ",
            "c) SG=\\(\\frac{V_{LOF}^2}{2g(A-BV^2)_{0.7V_{LOF}}}\\) ",
            "d) SG=\\(\\frac{V_{LOF}^2}{2g(A-BV^2)_{V_{LOF}}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for accelerating force is given by: \\(\\frac{F}{W}=\\Big\\{\\frac{F_N}{W}-\\mu_R-sin\\gamma_R\\Big\\}-\\frac{L}{W}\\Big(\\frac{C_D}{C_L}-\\mu_R\\Big)\\) where F is force, W is weight, μR is runway coefficient of the rolling friction, γR is runway slope, L is lift, CD and CL are the coefficients of drag and lift. The curly bracket in the accelerating force represents the net propulsive thrust- weight ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "The airborne distance is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2+V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "b) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N+D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2+V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "c) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N+D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "d) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for accelerating force is given by: \\(\\frac{F}{W}=\\Big\\{\\frac{F_N}{W}-\\mu_R-sin\\gamma_R\\Big\\}-\\frac{L}{W}\\Big(\\frac{C_D}{C_L}-\\mu_R\\Big)\\) where F is force, W is weight, μR is runway coefficient of the rolling friction, γR is runway slope, L is lift, CD and CL are the coefficients of drag and lift. The round bracket in the accelerating force represents the drag- lift ratio at the ground angle of attack.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "The energy change is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ΔE=\\(\\frac{T^2}{S^2}\\) ",
            "b) ΔE=\\(\\frac{T^2}{S}\\) ",
            "c) ΔE=\\(\\frac{T}{S}\\) ",
            "d) ΔE=T x S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula for ground run is given by the formula SG=\\(\\frac{V_{LOF}^2}{2g(A-BV^2)_{0.7V_{LOF}}}\\) where \n\nV is velocity\nG is acceleration due to gravity\nA and B are constants.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "What is the energy change in the aircraft when the thrust is 244N and the distance travelled is 1230km?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 198000 N-Km",
            "b) 484000 N-Km",
            "c) 300120 N-Km",
            "d) 234553 N-Km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The airborne distance is given by SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) where \n\nW is weight\nD is drag\nG is acceleration due to gravity\nV is velocity\nFN is normal force.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula of ground run distance with respect to aircraft weight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N+D+\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\) ",
            "b) SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N-D+\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\) ",
            "c) SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N+D-\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\) ",
            "d) SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N-D-\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two atmospheric effects on the take-off distances. They are:\n\nThe take-off with reference to the indicated airspeed\nThe output of the power plant which is roughly proportional to relative density.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula of airborne distance with respect to aircraft weight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2+V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "b) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N+D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2+V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "c) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N+D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "d) SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The formula for the ground run distance with respect to aircraft weight is given by SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N-D-\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\) where W is weight, V is velocity, L is lift, D is drag, g is acceleration due to gravity and μ is runway coefficient of rolling friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The airborne distance is given by SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) ",
            "b) The ground run distance is given by SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N-D-\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\) ",
            "c) The ground run distance is directly proportional to aircraft weight",
            "d) The ground run distance is directly proportional to aircraft drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The airborne distance is given by SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\) where \n\nW is weight\nD is drag\nG is acceleration due to gravity\nV is velocity\nFN is normal force.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "What is the use of the headwind?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To change the datum height",
            "b) To change the datum temperature",
            "c) To change the fuel ratio",
            "d) To change the pressure ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct statements are as follows:\n\nThe airborne distance is given by SA=\\(\\frac{W}{(F_N-D)_{av}}\\Big\\{\\frac{V_{2}^2-V_{LOF}^2}{2g}+35\\Big\\}\\)\nThe ground run distance is given by SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N-D-\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\)\nThe ground run distance is directly proportional to aircraft weight.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of the following will not effect the ground run distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TAS",
            "b) EAS",
            "c) Weight",
            "d) Thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The increase in aircraft weight by 10% will result in increase in aircraft ground run distance by 20%. The ground run distance is given by SG=\\(\\frac{WV_{LOF}^2}{2g[F_N-D-\\mu (W-L)]_{0.7V_{LOF}^2}}\\). From the formula it is known that the ground run distance is directly proportional to aircraft weight.\n"
    }
]